<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Trinitarian scheme of religion, concerning almighty God and mankind considered both before and after the (pretended) fall : with notes thereoupon, which notes contain also the unitarian scheme.</title>
            <author>Nye, Stephen, 1648?-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52616</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1509A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41717</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">31355819</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 31355819</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110696</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52616)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110696)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1750:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Trinitarian scheme of religion, concerning almighty God and mankind considered both before and after the (pretended) fall : with notes thereoupon, which notes contain also the unitarian scheme.</title>
                  <author>Nye, Stephen, 1648?-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the Year, 1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>This item also appears as part of A second collection of tracts ... London, 1693 (Wing S2267).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Trinity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Unitarianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Antitrinitarianism --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110696:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110696:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Trinitarian Scheme</hi> OF RELIGION, CONCERNING Almighty God; And MANKIND, Conſidered both before and after the (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended) <hi>Fall:</hi> With NOTES there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon; which Notes contain alſo the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarian</hi> Scheme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:110696:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:110696:2"/>
            <head>The <hi>Trinitarian</hi> Scheme of Religion concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Almighty God; and Mankind, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered both before and after the (pretended) <hi>Fall:</hi> with <hi>Notes</hi> thereupon; which Notes contain alſo the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarian</hi> Scheme.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> Trinity.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>THERE are Three <hi>Divine</hi> Perſons, an Almighty Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, an Almighty Son, an Almighty Spirit diſtinct from both, who are jointly <hi>Creators</hi> of all other, both Perſons and Things. They are ſo many diſtinct <hi>Minds</hi> and <hi>Spirits,</hi> indued each of them with his own <hi>Proper</hi> and <hi>Perſonal</hi> Underſtanding, Will, and Power of Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Each</hi> of them is an abſolutely Perfect and All-ſufficient Being; and <hi>ſingly</hi> and <hi>by himſelf</hi> a God. Yet all of them together are but one God.</q>
               </p>
               <div type="notes">
                  <head>The Notes.</head>
                  <p>There is <hi>a</hi> moſt Holy, moſt Wiſe, moſt Good and Almighty <hi>Perſon,</hi> who is over all, from everlaſting to everlaſting; the Maker of the Univerſe; the Fountain of Good to all other Beings, every where preſent. Who with reſpect to the Creation of the World, and his Adoption of all Good Men, is pleaſed to permit himſelf to be called <hi>the Father.</hi> But with reſpect to his Soveraign Dominion and Power above all, He is uſually deſigned by the Name or Word GOD.</p>
                  <p>There neither is nor can be more than one ſuch Perſon.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe He is All-ſufficient for himſelf, and for whatſoever He ſhall pleaſe to make; He had (thereby) within himſelf a moſt <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining</hi> and <hi>Certain</hi> Cauſe why he ſhould neither <hi>beget</hi> nor <hi>make</hi> another or others <hi>equal to Himſelf,</hi> but only Subordinate and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent Beings, for Objects and Exerciſes of his Goodneſs. More ſuch <hi>Perſons</hi> or <hi>Beings</hi> as Himſelf, He knew muſt be as needleſs and uſeleſs, as himſelf is abſolutely and indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſably neceſſary. For if He is <hi>truly</hi> All-ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, they muſt (for that reaſon) be <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together</hi> ſuperfluous, both to him and to his Creatures.</p>
                  <p>Nor can we ſuppoſe more than one ſuch Perſon, without ſuppoſing <hi>an Infinity</hi> of them. For whatſoever, either <hi>Rational Motive,</hi> or <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Neceſſary Cauſe,</hi> may be feigned; why the Univerſal Father ſhould beget or make another, or others, <hi>equal to Himſelf;</hi>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:110696:3"/>the ſame (whether Motive or Cauſe) muſt alſo diſpoſe that other, or thoſe other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to <hi>beget</hi> or <hi>make</hi> their Equal or Equals, and ſo onwards till there were an Infinity of Divine Perſons.</p>
                  <p>The Nature therefore of the thing <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtratively</hi> ſhows, that a ſtop is neceſſarily made at one Divine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that is, one Infinite and All-ſufficient Perſon.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the <hi>Eternity</hi> of the Trinity.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>AS to the Duration, Eternity or Life of the Bleſſed Trinity, the Trinity poſſeſſes Eternal Life <hi>all at once.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>To all other Beings, Time is a Flux or Succeſſion; that of it which was, now is not; and that which now is, ſhall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately give place to what is coming. It was once true of all other Beings but the Trinity, that they <hi>were, are</hi> and <hi>ſhall be;</hi> but to the Trinity there is neither paſt, nor to come, but whole Time or all Eternity is <hi>now.</hi> To the Trinity <hi>from everlaſting to everlaſting,</hi> is but one undivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Inſtant</hi> or <hi>Moment;</hi> for the Trinity <hi>is,</hi> we may not ſay <hi>it was,</hi> or <hi>it ſhall be.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <div type="notes">
                  <head>The Notes.</head>
                  <p>This Divinity is wholly borrowed from the <hi>Platoniſts;</hi> from whom the Modern Doctrines of the Trinity, and of the <hi>Myſtical</hi> Properties and Attributes thereof, have been learned by thoſe, who <hi>among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> go by the Names of <hi>Orthodox</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick.</hi> The Trinity, or God, ſay they, poſſeſſes Eternal Life <hi>all at once;</hi> He <hi>is,</hi> we may not ſay He <hi>was,</hi> or He <hi>ſhall be.</hi> In di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect oppoſition to this <hi>whimſical</hi> Paradox, St. <hi>John</hi> has defined God to be <hi>Him which WAS, which IS, and which SHALL BE,</hi> or <hi>is to come,</hi> Rev. 1.4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We ſay</hi> therefore, 'tis one of the Divine Perfections (not an Imperfection) that God <hi>IS, WAS</hi> and <hi>SHALL BE.</hi> He hath car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and ſhall carry all Perfections into all the Succeſſions and Periods of Time: when He <hi>WAS,</hi> he was no leſs perfect than now that he <hi>IS;</hi> nor is He now leſs perfect than he ſhall be when he <hi>SHALL BE.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They tell us, we muſt not ſay, <hi>God WAS;</hi> that is, to pleaſe them, we muſt turn Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts, by ſaying <hi>he WAS NOT;</hi> for of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty we muſt ſay one of the two, either that He <hi>was,</hi> or that He <hi>was not;</hi> there being no middle between theſe two, no more than there is between <hi>He is,</hi> and <hi>He is not.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the <hi>Omnipreſence</hi> and <hi>Infinity</hi> of the Trinity.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>NOR are we to conceive of the Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Immenſity or Omnipreſence of the Trinity after a vulgar manner. For tho the Trinity is truly Infinite and Omnipreſent, yet 'tis <hi>whole and all</hi> in any the leaſt Point of Space.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Trinity has <hi>no Extenſion,</hi> and yet it comprehends <hi>all Diſtances.</hi> The Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is three ſuch Perſons, as that each of them reaches <hi>over</hi> and <hi>through</hi> all the the World; and yet <hi>all Three are laxly and largely accommodated on the Point of a Needle.</hi> Not only ſo, but the right Faith is, the Trinity is <hi>no where,</hi> and yet 'tis <hi>every-where.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <div type="notes">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:110696:3"/>
                  <head>The Notes.</head>
                  <p>This is another Article of the new <hi>Plato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick</hi> Divinity: God, or the Trinity, ſay they, is <hi>whole and all</hi> in the leaſt point of Space; and tho he is <hi>no where,</hi> yet he is <hi>every-where.</hi> We ſay on the contrary (with St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>) what is <hi>no where,</hi> is <hi>nothing:</hi> therefore to ſpeak as they do of God, is <hi>in words</hi> to affirm him, and <hi>in ſenſe</hi> to deny him.</p>
                  <p>That God is <hi>every-where</hi> we are ready to demonſtrate to them, from the Order and Conſervation of his <hi>Works,</hi> and from the Effects of his <hi>Providence,</hi> and from an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Paſſages of Holy Scripture. That he is <hi>no where,</hi> is incumbent on them to prove; which we are ſure they can do by no <hi>Reaſon,</hi> nor by any <hi>Authority,</hi> but that of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters the <hi>Platoniſts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Every-where</hi> and <hi>no-where</hi> are <hi>contradictory</hi> Terms; therefore if God is every-where, it muſt needs be falſe that he is no-where: elſe we cannot diſtinguiſh between Affirming and Denying; that is, between expreſs Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the <hi>Simplicity</hi> of the Trinity.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>THere is no leſs Myſtery</hi> in the other Properties and Attributes of the Trinity. For God is one moſt ſimple <hi>uncompounded</hi> Being; yet He conſiſts, or is <hi>made up</hi> of Three really diſtinct Minds, Beings, or Spirits; ſo really diſtinct and <hi>diverſe,</hi> that <hi>one of them is not the other;</hi> nay, one is the Father, another <hi>his</hi> Son, the third a Spirit, as diſtinct from both, as they are from each other.</q>
               </p>
               <div type="notes">
                  <head>The Notes.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>There is no Myſtery at all</hi> in any of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties or Attributes of God. They are no leſs <hi>clear</hi> in themſelves, than they are <hi>evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently</hi> deduced from the Excellence of his <hi>Works,</hi> and the Methods of his <hi>Providence.</hi> The Myſtery never lies in the Attribute or Property, but in the Addition made to it by <hi>fanciful</hi> Men. As to that vulgar Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm, that God is a moſt ſimple and <hi>uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded</hi> Being, (from whence they have hammered the Property or Attribute of God's <hi>Simplicity,</hi> as they affect to ſpeak) 'tis not only <hi>not true,</hi> but ſelf-contradictory in the ſenſe they uſe it. For, how is God moſt ſimple and uncompounded, if he conſiſts or is <hi>made up</hi> (which is the very <hi>Engliſh</hi> of the word <hi>compounded</hi>) of diſtinct Beings, and divers and ſeveral Perſons, <hi>none of which is the other?</hi> They may with the ſame Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actneſs of Grammar, and Propriety of Speech, ſay, a <hi>Common-Council,</hi> or a <hi>Common-Hall,</hi> is one moſt ſimple uncompounded Being; one is no more ridiculous than the other: for the <hi>Propriety</hi> of Speech, and <hi>Exactneſs</hi> of Truth, is as verily loſt in <hi>three,</hi> as in <hi>three hundred,</hi> or <hi>three thouſand.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What is <hi>in</hi> God, is God.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>FOR the other Properties, 'tis the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox and true Belief, that <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is in God, is God.</hi> Not only the Father is God, and the Son is God, and the Holy Spirit is God; but whatſoever elſe is in God <hi>by way of Immanence,</hi> that alſo is God. So <hi>the Juſtice</hi> of God, is God; <hi>the Power</hi> of God, is God; <hi>the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110696:4"/>Wiſdom</hi> of God, is God; and ſo too is the Goodneſs of God.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Yet we make not hereby, ſo many ſeveral Gods; becauſe theſe and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Properties of God, are not only the ſame with him, but <hi>the ſame alſo with one another.</hi> The Juſtice (for inſtance) of God differs not <hi>really</hi> from his Power and Mercy: and his Power and Mercy differ not, or are not <hi>really</hi> diſtinguiſh'd from his Wiſdom, but are verily and identi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally the ſame with it, their diſtinction is only <hi>in our Conceit.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <div type="notes">
                  <head>The Notes.</head>
                  <p>See here another <hi>brace</hi> of <hi>Myſteries; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is in God, is God;</hi> and <hi>the Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties or Attributes differ not, but are the ſame with one another.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Reader may perhaps ſuſpect, that when they ſpeak after this <hi>wild</hi> faſhion, they have ſome <hi>ſecret</hi> and <hi>reſerved</hi> meaning, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the <hi>uſual</hi> Import of the Words, or a <hi>learned</hi> Senſe contrary to the <hi>vulgar</hi> Signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Terms: but 'tis not ſo, they mean as they ſpeak, and whole Volumes are written in Defence of theſe Follies.</p>
                  <p>But let us conſider what they ſay; <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is in God, is God; the Juſtice</hi> (for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) <hi>of God is God; and ſo alſo the other Properties and Attributes.</hi> As who ſhould ſay, every Property of a Being or Nature is that very Being or Nature, of which 'tis only a Property. This is more monſtrous than to ſay, <hi>a Part is the Whole,</hi> that very <hi>Whole</hi> of which 'tis only a <hi>Part.</hi> For a Property being ſomewhat leſs than an <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grating</hi> Part, becauſe it may be away, or at leaſt be dormant and unactive, without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Specifick Nature, or of the Perſon, an <hi>Integrating</hi> Part cannot; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'tis more abſurd to ſay, a Property, or Attribute is that very Being or Nature to which it belongs, than to ſay, an <hi>Integra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> Part is the <hi>Whole.</hi> Thus <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Soul</hi> are Integrating Parts of Man; take away one of them, and he is no longer a Man, but a naked Spirit; and <hi>Riſibility</hi> is an acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd <hi>Property</hi> of the Human Nature, and yet it may be dormant, or wholly away, and the Human Nature not be deſtroyed, but remain.</p>
                  <p>But they add, the Properties or Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes of God are <hi>the ſame with one another,</hi> they differ only in our Conceit.</p>
                  <p>But why do they not tell us too, that God pardons Sinners by his <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and puniſhes them by his <hi>Mercy;</hi> that he made the World by his <hi>Eternity,</hi> and will judg it by his <hi>Immenſity?</hi> For if Mercy and Juſtice, if Wiſdom and Power, if Eternity and Omnipreſence are the ſame, and <hi>differ only in our Conceit;</hi> then the Effects of any one of theſe Properties are not to be <hi>appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated</hi> to that Attribute or Property, but muſt be equally and indifferently aſcribed to all, or to any of the reſt.</p>
                  <p>Thus unlucky are our Oppoſers, both at <hi>dividing</hi> and <hi>compounding;</hi> they <hi>divide</hi> what is moſt intimately the ſame, and they <hi>compound,</hi> unite and identify what are and ever muſt be diverſe and different. That Unity of God (or that <hi>God is one</hi>) which ſhould have been as carefully guarded as the very Belief of a God, they have <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided,</hi> by introducing a Trinity of three equally All-mighty and All-ſufficient Perſons. And the Properties of the Divine Nature, to whoſe Diſtinction and Variety we muſt heedfully attend, if we will have any ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate Notion of God, or right Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of his Works and Providences, theſe they <hi>confound,</hi> by affirming they are the ſame. But let us go on to what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:110696:4"/>
               <head>What we are to underſtand by the <hi>Son</hi> and <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <q>GOD is <hi>one ſubſtantial and moſt ſimple Act;</hi> yet we ſay alſo God is <hi>two ſubſtantial and really diſtinct Acts.</hi> The two ſubſtantial and immanent Acts in God, are <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> and <hi>Will.</hi> For God moſt perfectly <hi>underſtands</hi> himſelf, and alſo <hi>willeth</hi> (that is, loveth) him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the moſt perfect manner.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>But whatſoever underſtandeth, doth underſtand by <hi>conceiving</hi> an Image of the thing underſtood. Therefore God (as hath been ſaid) underſtanding himſelf from all Eternity, <hi>conceived</hi> within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from all Eternity a moſt perfect <hi>Image</hi> of himſelf. Which Image thus <hi>conceived,</hi> and (as it were) <hi>generated</hi> or <hi>begotten</hi> by him, is called <hi>the Son.</hi> And this Image being <hi>in</hi> God, and <hi>a perfect</hi> Image of God, and <hi>Eternal,</hi> is God no leſs than <hi>the Father,</hi> by whom it was conceived or generated in the manner aforeſaid; namely, by his underſtanding or appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending himſelf, and his own Perfections.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>But God alſo <hi>willeth,</hi> and that is another of <hi>the ſubſtantial immanent Acts</hi> that concur to the eſſentiating the Trinity. He <hi>willeth</hi> or loveth himſelf, and the moſt perfect Image of himſelf; and the Image <hi>willeth</hi> or loveth him. This <hi>Mutual Love</hi> of the Father, and the Image (or <hi>Son</hi>) is what is named <hi>the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> So that what things in Men are <hi>Faculties, Actions</hi> and <hi>Properties,</hi> in God we muſt underſtand them to be <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Spirits.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Which is alſo farther both cleared and proved, by this Obſervation. The ſecond Perſon, or <hi>Son,</hi> is the Underſtanding or Wiſdom of God; not <hi>Original Wiſdom,</hi> or Underſtanding, for that is the Father; but <hi>a reflex Wiſdom,</hi> that is, the Wiſdom which reſulteth from the Father's under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding himſelf, and his own Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The Holy Spirit (as hath been ſaid) is the mutual, willing, Love and Power of <hi>Original Wiſdom,</hi> and of the <hi>Reflex Wiſdom.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <div type="notes">
                  <head>The Notes.</head>
                  <p>This they pretend is that <hi>Myſtery hid from Ages and Generations, but now made manifeſt</hi> to the Diſciples of <hi>Athanaſius.</hi> There is no Parallel for it in all either Hiſtory or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but the Myſteries of the <hi>Egyptians.</hi> For as the <hi>Egyptians</hi> were at prodigious Coſt, in making and ſetting up a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Images <hi>in</hi> and <hi>about</hi> their Temples, by which <hi>Hieroglyphicks,</hi> or ſacred Images, they pretended to teach Men the Secrets of <hi>Natural Philoſophy,</hi> and the Precepts of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality;</hi> but when they were ask'd to explain the meaning of theſe <hi>Hieroglyphicks,</hi> they gave a very <hi>mean</hi> and <hi>trifling</hi> Senſe, or a Senſe very <hi>abſurd</hi> and <hi>falſe.</hi> So after Trinitarians have long amuſed their Diſciples with Terms as <hi>Myſtical</hi> as the <hi>Egyptian Hieroglyphicks,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Trinity, Eternal Generation, Eternal Proceſſion, three Infinite Perſons and but one God:</hi> Ask them, <hi>How can theſe things be,</hi> and what do you mean? They anſwer, our meaning only is, God <hi>underſtands</hi> himſelf, and <hi>willeth</hi> (that is, eſteems and loves) himſelf. This is a very mean and deſpicable Senſe, to be couched in ſuch <hi>myſterious</hi> and <hi>ſurpriſing</hi> Terms: Why do they affect to ſpeak <hi>fantaſtically,</hi> when they might ſpeak <hi>ſoberly</hi> and <hi>plainly?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But we would eaſily forgive them <hi>the Folly</hi> of their Myſteries, if their <hi>Hieroglyphick Language</hi> were not as falſe and contradictory as 'tis vain and trifling. For after they have told us, that by <hi>Son</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> they mean nothing but God's <hi>Knowledg</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> of himſelf; that <hi>the Eternal Generation</hi> (ſo much talk'd of) is only God's <hi>conceiving, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</hi> or apprehending his own Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and <hi>the Proceſſion</hi> (which we are ſo carefully to diſtinguiſh from the <hi>Eternal Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration</hi>) is only <hi>the Love</hi> which <hi>proceeds</hi> from
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110696:5"/>God towards himſelf: after (I ſay) they have thus unriddled their <hi>Myſtery,</hi> and of a Myſtery, made it a very vulgar and ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry piece of Knowledg; how abſurd and monſtrous is it to tell us, that this Reflex <hi>Knowledg</hi> which God hath of himſelf, and his <hi>Love</hi> or Eſteem of himſelf, are <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Spirits</hi> really diſtinct from <hi>him?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>One while the Second and Third Perſons (ſo called) are only God's <hi>knowing</hi> himſelf, and <hi>loving</hi> himſelf; that is, they are only <hi>two Acts of his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding and Will.</hi> At the next turn, theſe two Acts, God's <hi>Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending</hi> himſelf, and <hi>Eſteeming</hi> himſelf, are metamorphoſed into Two ſeveral <hi>Spirits</hi> and <hi>Perſons;</hi> whereof one you muſt call <hi>the Son,</hi> and the other <hi>the Holy Ghoſt:</hi> Of one you muſt ſay, on pain of Damnation, He was <hi>Conceived,</hi> Generated or Begotten; of the other you muſt believe and ſay, under the ſame Penalty, He <hi>proceeded.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I ſay now, this is <hi>Egyptian</hi> all over; 'tis the very Genius and Spirit of the old My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical <hi>Hieroglyphicks,</hi> that is to ſay, partly <hi>Fooliſh,</hi> and partly <hi>Falſe.</hi> And to prove it, I need go no farther, than the Underſtandings and Conſciences of all Reaſonable Men; or even of every Individual Man, who hath not as much given up his <hi>Reaſon</hi> to Mother-<hi>Church,</hi> as the Good Man who would not believe his Eyes againſt his Dear Wife, had given up to her his <hi>Senſes.</hi> To tell Men, that to <hi>apprehend</hi> one's ſelf is <hi>a Perſon;</hi> and to love one's ſelf, is another <hi>Perſon</hi> and <hi>Spirit;</hi> is (in effect) to ridicule Religion, and to ſcare from it all Men of free Senſe.</p>
                  <p>I know not why the prophane <hi>Wit</hi> was eſteemed an Atheiſt, for his ſaying, God by his Almighty Power can turn <hi>a Tree into a Syllogiſm;</hi> more than ſuch may be juſtly ſuſpected of Atheiſm, who ſay, an Action of the Divine <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> is an Infinite and Almighty <hi>Perſon,</hi> whom under pain of Damnation we muſt call <hi>the Son of God:</hi> And again, an Action of the Divine <hi>Will</hi> is another ſuch <hi>Perſon,</hi> and him we muſt name <hi>the Holy Ghoſt?</hi> For <hi>the Wit</hi> only turned <hi>a Subſtance</hi> into <hi>a Thought;</hi> and Trinitarians turn <hi>Thoughts</hi> into <hi>Subſtances</hi> and <hi>Perſons.</hi> Did they alledg for theſe Myſteries, but the leaſt colour of <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Revelation,</hi> we would hold our Tongues; but to be obliged to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve ſuch things, without any pretence of <hi>Revelation,</hi> and contrary to all <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>common Senſe,</hi> this (I think) is what we owe to no ſort of Men, of what colour ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they dye their Coats.</p>
                  <p>For my part I never think of theſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Dotages</hi> or <hi>Impoſtures,</hi> without ſuch an Inclination as I very hardly reſiſt, of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying to our <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Doctors, what <hi>Cato</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Roman Augures</hi> and <hi>Auriſpices.</hi> I wonder, ſays <hi>Cato,</hi> that an <hi>Augur</hi> or <hi>Aruſpex,</hi> can meet another of the ſame Profeſſion, without their Laughing in one another's Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. He knew their (pretended) Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Diſcipline, was <hi>the Religion eſtabliſh'd by Law; warranted by Cuſtom and Preſcription; and authorized by the Conſent of Nations.</hi> For all that, 'twas a Cheat ſo groſs and palpable, that he could not but admire, that the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurs</hi> were ſuch <hi>ſtark</hi> Fools, or ſuch <hi>perfect</hi> Knaves, that (meeting) they could carry a grave Look upon one another.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Creation.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>IN the Fulneſs of Time, the before-deſcribed <hi>Trinity</hi> Created the World, and all things therein. Yet we are not to imagine, that the Three Divine Perſons <hi>divided</hi> the Work among them, each of them taking a Part. Nor could every one of them Create the ſame things, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a thing can be created but once. But according to that <hi>Oeconomy,</hi> as <hi>Divines</hi> ſpeak (that is, the Domeſtick Order, or
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110696:5"/>
                     <hi>Houſhold-Government</hi>) that is between the Three Perſons, it muſt be ſaid and held, that <hi>the Father</hi> is moſt <hi>properly</hi> the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, <hi>the Son</hi> the Redeemer, and <hi>the Spirit</hi> the Sanctifier, of all Perſons and Things. So that when we ſay, the Trinity Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Heaven and Earth, and all Things, this is thereby intended; The Father Created all things, <hi>by</hi> the Son, <hi>through</hi> the Holy Ghoſt.</q>
               </p>
               <div type="notes">
                  <head>The Notes.</head>
                  <p>The Father created all things <hi>by</hi> the Son, <hi>through</hi> the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>I wiſh <hi>the Sages</hi> of the Party had thought fit <hi>plainly</hi> to tell us what they mean, by ſuch an <hi>odd</hi> way of expreſſing themſelves. But they have long ſince let the World know that all their care is to get <hi>Words;</hi> and for <hi>Meaning,</hi> they never think of it.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>the Father</hi> it ſeems is the Creator; nay, 'tis he that is <hi>properly</hi> the Creator: but then 'tis <hi>by</hi> the Son, and <hi>through</hi> the Holy Ghoſt. That is to ſay, <hi>the Father is not the Creator,</hi> much leſs is He <hi>properly</hi> the Creator, but the Son and Holy Ghoſt; and theſe two are <hi>jointly</hi> Creators. For if the Father crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the World <hi>by</hi> the Son, and <hi>through</hi> the Holy Ghoſt; then the Father himſelf had no <hi>immediate</hi> Efficiency, or Hand in the Work, but only the Son and Holy Ghoſt: theſe were the <hi>true</hi> Creators of the World, and of all things. And beſides that, the old Difficulty returns; namely, that the Son and Spirit divided the Work between them, each taking his part; or the ſame things muſt be created <hi>twice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I know not how better to explain their Notion, of the <hi>Father</hi>'s being moſt <hi>properly</hi> the Creator, than by ſaying, he was juſt ſo (according to them) the Creator of the World, as King <hi>Charles</hi> I. built <hi>the Royal Soveraign,</hi> or was the Builder of <hi>the Royal Soveraign.</hi> For we ſay that King built <hi>the Royal Soveraign, by</hi> the Maſter-Builder, <hi>through</hi> the Ship-Carpenter; that is, <hi>he built it not,</hi> he only ordered it to be built, the Maſter-Shipwright (or Maſter-Builder) and the Ship-Carpenters were the Builders.</p>
                  <p>But if this be ſo, we are ſtrangely miſled by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Creed, which inſtructs us to ſay, that <hi>the Almighty Father</hi> is the Creator of Heaven and Earth, and is wholly ſilent of the great <hi>Myſtery,</hi> that it was <hi>by</hi> the Son, and <hi>through</hi> the Holy Ghoſt. And the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures do yet worſe impoſe on us by an <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard-of</hi> Soleciſm and Impropriety, while they ſpeak of theſe <hi>two</hi> (or <hi>three</hi>) pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>creating</hi> Perſons, by the ſingular Pronouns <hi>I, HE, THO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>, HIM,</hi> which in no Language are uſed, but only of one ſingular and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <hi>Perſon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They confound us yet more, if more can be, by telling us <hi>only</hi> (and <hi>ſo often</hi>) of the Creator, never of <hi>Creators,</hi> as Trinitarians would have us to ſpeak. Gen. 6.7. <hi>Jebovah ſaid,</hi> I <hi>will deſtroy Man, whom</hi> I <hi>have made.</hi> Iſa. 42.5. <hi>HE that created the Heavens,—HE that ſpread out the Earth, HE that giveth Breath unto the People.</hi> Nehem. 9.6. <hi>THO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> haſt made the Heaven, the Heaven of Heavens, with all their Hoſt; the Earth, and all things therein; the Sea, and all that is therein; and THO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> preſerveſt them all; and the Hoſt of Heaven worſhippeth THEE.</hi> This Text aſſures us there was no <hi>dividing</hi> the work between two, or more <hi>Perſons.</hi> It was one THOU who both <hi>created</hi> and <hi>preſerves</hi> all things: and THEE, ſaith the Text, the the Hoſt of Heaven worſhippeth, not YE, not THEM, not more Perſons, but one only. Iſa. 4.28. <hi>The CREATOR of the Ends of the Earth fainteth not.</hi> Rom. 1.25. <hi>Served the Creature more than</hi> (Gr. beſides) <hi>the CREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TOR.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But what is not (really) found in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for their purpoſe, Trinitarians know how to diſcover that 'tis there; which, with reſpect to the caſe before us, they do theſe two ways. Firſt, by interpreting the Texts, which <hi>by Confeſſion of their ableſt Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> ſpeak of <hi>the new Creation,</hi> (or Reno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the World from Idolatry, to the Knowledg of the one true God) which was <hi>by Chriſt,</hi> concerning <hi>the old Creation,</hi> (or
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110696:6"/>the making of Heaven and Earth) which was <hi>by God.</hi> Secondly, They oft-times <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly</hi> add the word or words that were wanting on their behalf, which they have done in abundance of Contexts. But for both theſe Artifices (their Detection and their Confutation) I refer to <hi>the brief Hiſtory of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of <hi>Original</hi> Sin.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>SOon after the Creation, <hi>Adam,</hi> the firſt Man, tranſgreſſing the Law given to him of not eating the forbidden Fruit; he thereby incurred the Penalty of Death, that was the Penalty annex'd to the Law, which he had violated. But, firſt, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred this Penalty, not only for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who was the <hi>actual</hi> and <hi>real</hi> Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but for his whole Poſterity: God <hi>impating</hi> to them, or <hi>reckoning</hi> to them his Offence, as if they had been the Doers of it. Secondly, We are to know, that in the word <hi>Death</hi> there is implied, not only what is naturally and commonly meant thereby, even the Separation of the Soul from the Body, and the Body's returning to Duſt; but, firſt, ſuch a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and Depravation of our Faculties, that we are all born naturally averſe from <hi>every</hi> good Word and Work, and inclined to Evil <hi>only,</hi> and to <hi>all</hi> kinds of Evil. <hi>Then</hi> all <hi>Temporal</hi> Calamities and Evils, to which human Life is ſubject; and <hi>finally,</hi> Eternal <hi>Damnation.</hi> All theſe are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in the words of the Sanction, <hi>The day thou eateſt thereof, thou ſhalt die;</hi> and they are by <hi>Divines</hi> commonly called the three Deaths, or the threefold Death, <hi>Spiritual, Temporal</hi> and <hi>Eternal.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>But we mean not to ſay, that the word <hi>Death</hi> doth in its firſt or proper Signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, import all the aboveſaid Evils. But it pleaſed God when He paſſed Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence on <hi>Adam, to extend the Signification of that Word,</hi> which expreſt and contained the Penalty of his Law.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>'Tis true, 'twould be cried out on, as moſt unjuſt among Men, to reckon or impute the Tranſgreſſion of a Father to his Children, and other Poſterity; and much more, if they were puniſh'd for it in a far more extream manner than is truly and indeed implied in the Penalty annex'd to the Law that was violated; that is, if the Word or Words of the Penalty were <hi>extended</hi> and <hi>ſtrained</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond their proper and natural meaning. Yet theſe things cannot be unjuſt with God, becauſe He can do no Unjuſtice; and the reaſon of that is, becauſe <hi>Things or Actions are not juſt or unjuſt in themſelves, or in their own Natures, but only as God, who hath all Authority and Power, either willeth and commandeth them, or (on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary) nilleth and forbiddeth them.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <div type="notes">
                  <head>The Notes.</head>
                  <p>This <hi>Poſtulatum,</hi> that Things or Actions are not juſt or unjuſt in themſelves, or in their own Natures, but only as the Supream Authority and Power (that is to ſay, GOD) ſhall pleaſe to <hi>will</hi> or <hi>nill</hi> them, to <hi>command</hi> or <hi>forbid</hi> them, is indeed neceſſary to the Defence of ſuch Doctrines as theſe, that God doth <hi>arbitrarily</hi> impute the Sin of <hi>one</hi> Man to <hi>all</hi> Men; and that in puniſhing thoſe whom he hath made guilty by his meer <hi>Will,</hi> he infinitely exceeds the true proper and natural Signification of the Words in <hi>the Sanction,</hi> that is, of the words of that part of his Law, which contain <hi>the Penalty</hi> of tranſgreſſing it. That <hi>Poſtulatum</hi> is ſo neceſſary to this Doctrine of <hi>Original</hi> Sin, that it muſt be owned, that the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> have judged better, and ſpoke more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtently
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110696:6"/>than their Oppoſers of ſome other Sects and Churches, who hold <hi>Original</hi> Sin as 'tis before deſcribed, and yet ſeem un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to allow of that only <hi>Baſis</hi> on which (<hi>Calviniſts</hi> have rightly ſeen) it will ſtand; namely this, that Juſt and Unjuſt, Good and Evil, are only the Will and Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him that hath Supream Power. But as the <hi>Poſtulatum</hi> is neceſſary to the Doctrine for which it was deviſed; ſo it as much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys <hi>the Eternal Rectitude and Holineſs of God,</hi> as the Doctrines in the foregoing Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraphs, which have been already conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, overthrow the Unity, the Omnipre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and other his Eſſential Perfections and Attributes.</p>
                  <p>It is horrible but to think that theſe Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations on the moſt Holy God, are ſuch, as would make up the <hi>juſt</hi> Character of <hi>an Almighty Devil.</hi> For if the Devil had Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Power, what worſe could he do, than <hi>they feign</hi> is done, by the Fountain it ſelf of Rectitude and Holineſs? Could he do worſe than impute the Sin of <hi>one</hi> Man to <hi>all</hi> Men, and puniſh them for it, (<hi>beſides</hi> and <hi>beyond</hi> his own Sanction) with an utter Inability to all that is good, <hi>then</hi> puniſh Inability (which was neither their Act nor Deſert, and of which himſelf was the only cauſe) with Eternal Damnation?</p>
                  <p>Here many to help themſelves a little, ſay, God ſaves <hi>ſome</hi> from this Ruine; he reſcues his <hi>Elect,</hi> tho not from Sin and <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral</hi> Death and Calamity, yet from <hi>Eternal</hi> Damnation; nay, beſtows on them the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable and everlaſting Beatitudes of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
                  <p>But this is no better than the other: For the higheſt Injuſtice to the far-greater number, is ſo far from being excuſed, by <hi>an ungrounded Partiality</hi> for a very few, that this latter may be truly called a <hi>new</hi> and <hi>freſh</hi> Inſtance of ſort of Unjuſtice. Is it not <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſtice</hi> too, to make a great number of Creatures of the ſame kind; and tho one deſerves no more than another of them, either for Good or Evil; cheriſh one with whatſoever <hi>Omnipotence</hi> can do for him, and burn againſt the other with Wrath eternal and inſupportable?</p>
                  <p>But they ſay, God having all Authority and Power, what He <hi>willeth</hi> muſt needs be Law, that is to ſay, <hi>Juſtice;</hi> and what He <hi>nills,</hi> or forbids, muſt be Tranſgreſſion, that is to ſay, <hi>Evil, Sin</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſtice.</hi> But from thence, it unavoidably follows, that the Devil wants nothing but <hi>Supream Power</hi> to legitimate all his Wickedneſs, and to change the nature of it from Wickedneſs to Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. If that Spirit had Supream Power, we muſt call him, as we now do, GOD, moſt Holy, moſt Juſt, moſt Righteous. And ſeeing God hath all Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, it would (on this Hypotheſis) be in him <hi>Righteous, Good</hi> and <hi>Praiſe-worthy,</hi> if He were pleaſed to damn his moſt faithful Servants, to break the Covenant, and diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the Hopes of Life and Happineſs, which he hath confirmed by his <hi>Oath;</hi> and (on the contrary) ſhould think fit to ſave not only the moſt Godleſs and Impious Men, but the very Devils. Theſe Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences are unavoidable on the before-ſaid Hypotheſis, or Doctrine, that Things and Actions are not Good or Evil in themſelves, but only by the Will of Supream Power; and they that <hi>admit</hi> of ſuch Conſequences, or cannot <hi>decline</hi> them, how can they be diſputed with? But let us ſee what is the Doctrine of the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> concerning the firſt Sin, or (pretended) Fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> and the Conſequences thereof.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians teach concerning the Sin of <hi>Adam,</hi> and the Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces thereon.</head>
               <p>WE <hi>ſay,</hi> when Almighty God had formed the Protoplaſts, <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> He forthwith declared them Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Lords of whatſoever is in the Earth or Seas. Gen. 1.28. <hi>Have Dominion,</hi> ſaith God there to them, <hi>over the Fiſh of the Sea, over the Fowl of the Air, and over every living thing that moveth on the Earth. And I have
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110696:7"/>given you every Herb, — and every Tree. Adam</hi> having thus received from his unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Maker, ſuch Marks of his Favour, was admoniſh'd withal, that he muſt remember he is <hi>a Creature,</hi> and has received of another whatſoever he <hi>is,</hi> or <hi>hath.</hi> Notwithſtanding thou haſt to deal with ſuch a Soveraign, as will not require of thee <hi>unreaſonable</hi> or <hi>troubleſom</hi> Teſtimonies of thy Regards and Reſpects to him. See, the whole World is before thee, and it is all given to thee; only in this Paradiſe there is one Fruit, the Fruit of the Tree of Knowledg, of that thou art not to eat. 'Tis <hi>the Obedience</hi> that thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker requires of thee; 'tis the only Trial his Goodneſs is pleaſed to make of thy Love and Duty to him. If thou breakeſt this Charge, the Penalty is, that thy Life <hi>preſently</hi> departs from thee; <hi>the day</hi> thou eateſt thereof, thou ſhalt <hi>die;</hi> that is, ſhalt <hi>return to Duſt, from whence</hi> as much of thee as is viſible, and as thou art yet aware of, <hi>was taken.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It cannot be denied that this was the moſt <hi>proper</hi> of all Trials, the moſt <hi>prudent</hi> of all Commands. <hi>Adam</hi> could not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid to commit <hi>Adultery</hi> or <hi>Fornication,</hi> there being but one Woman, and ſhe alſo his Wife; or <hi>Murder,</hi> becauſe he had too much occaſion for <hi>Evt,</hi> and ſhe for him, to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſuch Thoughts; or <hi>Theft,</hi> for all the World was theirs. But he was <hi>thorowly</hi> tried by the Prohibition of the Tree of <hi>Knowledg,</hi> becauſe of our natural Thirſt of <hi>Knowledg,</hi> and the Ambition all have to be <hi>wiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not neceſſary however to determine, whether the forbidden Fruit had indeed a Power to ſharpen the Faculties of the Mind, Underſtanding and Memory? 'Twas ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for the Trial God deſigned to make of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Obedience, only to name or call that Fruit, <hi>the Fruit of the Tree of Knowledg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There was nothing more juſt, than that <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould be ſatisfied with the great Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages he already poſſeſt; for all the Creatures, whether Animate, or Inanimate, were his; and he could not but be ſenſible, that his <hi>preſent</hi> Knowledg or Underſtanding was ſufficient, both for himſelf and them. But <hi>Adam</hi> was perſwaded by <hi>Satan</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour himſelf to make himſelf more like to <hi>Elohim, i. e.</hi> to the Angels and Spirits of Heaven, by the uſe of the forbidden Fruit. <hi>Thou ſhalt know,</hi> ſaith the Tempter, if thou follow my Counſel, <hi>Good and Evil;</hi> the meaning ſeemeth to be, Thou ſhalt know whatſoever Good and Evil is in every thing, by the uſe of this happy Fruit. He that forbids thee this Fruit, has confeſt its Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, in the Name he was given to it; why therefore has he forbad it to thee, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is <hi>envious, jealous</hi> or <hi>moroſe? Ye ſhall not ſurely die</hi> by eating this Fruit: for how ſhould it be more mortal to you, than to the Serpent, and to ſo many other Beaſts and Birds as daily gather it up?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adam</hi> hearkens to theſe, and ſuch like Reaſonings, eats the forbidden Fruit, and thereby becomes obnoxious to the Penalty, even <hi>preſent</hi> Death.</p>
               <p>But it pleaſed God to defer the threatned Puniſhment or Penalty, he deferred it for upwards of nine hundred Years, which ſeem to be Lunar Years, that is <hi>Months,</hi> notwithſtanding what Dr. <hi>Lightfoot</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have urged, for ſuch kind of Years as are now in uſe. Their Arguments are partly Miſtakes, partly Inadvertences, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly groundleſs Conjectures.</p>
               <p>But tho the threatned Puniſhment was not preſently executed on <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve;</hi> yet the Wiſdom of God did not think fit to incourage Sin, by wholly paſſing over this beginning of it. He puniſh'd <hi>Adam,</hi> and <hi>caution'd</hi> his Poſterity, by curſing the Earth; that is, by cauſing it to bring forth Thorns and Thiſtles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as well as profitable Seeds and Plants: ſo that <hi>Adam</hi> and his Deſcendents muſt now <hi>Manure</hi> and <hi>Till</hi> the Ground, if they would have a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular</hi> Harveſt of Seeds and Fruits. Againſt <hi>Eve</hi> he pronounced, that whereas Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving and Child-bearing are naturally and neceſſarily both ſickly and painful in ſome degree; yet both theſe ſhould be more
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110696:7"/>troubleſome to her, than uſual or natural. <hi>I will GREATLY multiply thy Sorrows in thy Conception; and with Sorrow ſhalt thou bring forth,</hi> ſaith the Angel who repreſented God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.16.</p>
               <p>The Holy Scriptures go no farther than this, in the account they give of the Sin of <hi>Adam,</hi> and the Puniſhment and Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences thereof, ſaving that they expreſly contradict the Doctrine of Trinitarians, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a threefold Death, Temporal, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Eternal, which was inflicted (they ſay) on <hi>Adam,</hi> and on all his Deſcendents for his Sin.</p>
               <p>Where ſhall we look for the true Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation or Meaning of the <hi>Penalty</hi> or Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment annex'd to a Law, but in <hi>the Sentence</hi> which the Judg and Lawgiver himſelf paſſes on the Offender? <hi>The Law</hi> was this, <hi>The day thou eateſt thereof</hi> (of the forbidden Fruit) <hi>thou ſhalt die,</hi> Gen. 2.17. that is, ſay the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians, Thou ſhalt return to Duſt;</hi> thy Life and Spirit ſhall leave thy Body, and be diſpoſed of as ſhall ſeem good to thy Maker, who in Judgment always remembers Mercy. Let us now ſee in <hi>the Sentence,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this was not indeed <hi>the whole meaning</hi> of theſe words of the Law, <hi>Thou ſhalt die?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Gen. 3.19. <hi>Duſt thou art, and to Duſt thou ſhalt return.</hi> Here is the evident Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Mouth of the Judg and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver giving Sentence, what was meant by <hi>the day thou eateſt thereof, thou ſhalt DIE.</hi> And this Penalty, Puniſhment and Sentence was at length executed on <hi>Adam,</hi> tho he had the favour of a long Reprieve, a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieve of about <hi>Eighty</hi> Years.</p>
               <p>Our Oppoſers can ſhow no Context of Holy Scripture, in which their threefold Death (for this Sin) is contained; or in which the Poſterity of <hi>Adam</hi> are ſaid to have his Sin imputed to them, and that they are puniſh'd for it.</p>
               <p>The only Offer they make is, from <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> Chap. 5. the Apoſtle there (at <hi>v.</hi> 19.) ſaith, <hi>As by one Man's Diſobedience, many are made Sinners; ſo by the Obedience of one ſhall many be made Righteous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By one Man's Diſobedience,</hi> ſay they, that is, by God's Imputation of one Man's Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience to them, (even <hi>Adam</hi>'s in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe) ſo many have been made Sinners. How much more <hi>dexterouſly,</hi> and <hi>agreeably</hi> to the Juſtice and Wiſdom of God, <hi>Pelagius</hi> and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians? By one Man's Diſobedience,</hi> that is, ſaith <hi>Pelagius,</hi> not as <hi>Auſtin</hi> has <hi>newly</hi> fancied, <hi>by God's Imputation,</hi> but <hi>by our Imitation</hi> of one Man's Diſobedience, ſo many have been made Sinners: and on the other hand, <hi>by the Obedience of one;</hi> that is, <hi>by Imitation</hi> (not by Imputation) <hi>of one Man's Obedience,</hi> even the Lord Chriſt's, many ſhall be made Righteous.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Trinitarians</hi> make the ſame Blunder at ver. 18. <hi>As by the Offence of one, Judgment came upon all Men to Condemnation: even ſo by the Righteouſneſs of one, the free Gift came</hi> (or ſhall come) <hi>upon all Men to Juſtification and Life.</hi> Here again they ſee not, that <hi>by the Offence of one Man,</hi> and again, <hi>by the Righteouſneſs of one Man,</hi> are not as much as to ſay, <hi>by the Imputation</hi> of one Man's Offence, and of one Man's Righteouſneſs; but <hi>by Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> of one Man's Righteouſneſs, and of another Man's Offence, Juſtification and Condemnation have come upon all Men. We <hi>die</hi> for imitating the Diſobedience of <hi>Adam;</hi> and we ſhall be juſtified and ſaved <hi>for</hi> and <hi>by imitating</hi> the Righteouſneſs of the Lord Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And thus it is, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains himſelf in this very Chapter, <hi>v.</hi> 12. <hi>As by one Man Sin entred into the World, and Death by Sin: ſo alſo Death hath paſſed upon all Men; for that</hi> (or, becauſe) <hi>all have ſinned.</hi> He ſaith not, as Trinitarians do, becauſe <hi>Adam</hi> ſinned; but <hi>becauſe all have ſinned,</hi> therefore Death hath paſſed on all; that is, all of us have deſerved the Death we muſt undergo, or have undergone, by our own Sins.</p>
               <p>But they ſay <hi>Infants</hi> die, and what Sin have they, unleſs you allow <hi>the Imputation</hi> of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Sin to all his Deſcendents?</p>
               <p>But why do they not conſider too, that <hi>Beaſts</hi> die; is <hi>Adam</hi>'s Sin Imputed alſo to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110696:8"/>them? They ought therefore to know, that Holy <hi>Paul</hi> in that Context is ſpeaking only of <hi>Adult</hi> and <hi>Grown</hi> Perſons: as for Infants, Beaſts, and ſuch like, that have not Sin; becauſe they have not <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> of Good and Evil, of Moral and Immoral; ſuch die, becauſe they have <hi>Mortal</hi> Bodies, liable to Diſeaſes and Accidents. From which (Accidents and Diſeaſes) to deliver and reſcue them, it does not pleaſe God to Interpoſe, by an <hi>Extraordinary</hi> and <hi>Miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous</hi> Power. For which ſort of Providence towards them, divers <hi>Probable</hi> Reaſons might be given: but being not Neceſſary or Proper to be here inſerted, I omit them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of <hi>Partial</hi> Redemption.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>THE Tranſgreſſion of <hi>Adam</hi> in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, or his eating the Forbidden Fruit, was in Him <hi>Actual</hi> Sin; in his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendents 'tis called <hi>Original</hi> Sin: but the Effects of it, are the ſame in Both; namely, the before-mentioned three-fold Death, or three Deaths. <hi>Death Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> which is the ſeparation of the Soul from the Body, and all temporal Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities and Evils. <hi>Death Spiritual,</hi> which is the Corruption of the Faculties, that we are averſe to <hi>all</hi> Good, and inclined to <hi>all</hi> Evil. <hi>Death Eternal,</hi> which is the everlaſting Suffering of Body and Soul in Hell-fire. Theſe Deaths are <hi>the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences</hi> and <hi>Deſert</hi> of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Sin; to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as the <hi>Actual</hi> Offender; to us, as his Sin is <hi>Imputed</hi> to us by <hi>the Juſtice</hi> of God.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>But the <hi>Mercy</hi> of God, and his <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> have found out a moſt Gracious and Glorious <hi>Expedient,</hi> by which to deliver Mankind, though not from <hi>Temporal</hi> Death, yet (in part) from <hi>Spiritual</hi> Death, and (wholly and altogether) from Death <hi>Eternal.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>But before we ſpeak more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the <hi>Expedient;</hi> 'tis neceſſary to caution <hi>Learners,</hi> that they fall not into this Error; that God deſigned the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Expedient, for <hi>All</hi> Men and Women. For when we ſay, Mankind, or <hi>all</hi> Men have been Redeemed, from the before-mentioned Deaths; our mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, that <hi>the Elect,</hi> (or as that moſt conſider'd and weigh'd <hi>17<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                     </hi> Article of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church ſpeaks) <hi>Thoſe whom God hath choſen out of Mankind, are</hi> (as that Article farther ſays) <hi>brought to ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Salvation, as Veſſels of Honour. Theſe are called, according to God's purpoſe, in due Seaſon; his Spirit working in them. And they, through Grace, obey that Calling.</hi> Theſe <hi>Elect</hi> are a definite, certain, and unalterable Number, that can neither be increaſed, nor diminiſhed; as is Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and in words declared, by <hi>the Suffrage</hi> of the Divines of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> at the Synod of <hi>Dort; Suffrage,</hi> p. 9. It is (ſaith the ſame <hi>Suffrage</hi> at p. 43.) for <hi>the Elect</hi> that Chriſt died; that He might <hi>Effectually</hi> obtain for them, and <hi>Infallibly</hi> beſtow on them, both Remiſſion of Sins, and Salvation.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>If the Unskilful ask here; How this Doctrine agreeth with thoſe Declarations of Holy Scripture, ſo often repeated; which ſeem to ſay, that Chriſt died for the Sins of <hi>the World,</hi> or for <hi>All</hi> Men? The Divines (above ſaid) anſwer at <hi>p.</hi> 47. Here it is, that the ſecret Decree of Election ſheweth it ſelf: inaſmuch as the Price was indeed payed for All, yet is not Beneficial to All; becauſe All have not <hi>the Giſt</hi> of fulfilling the Condition of the Covenant. They mean; All have not <hi>Saving Grace</hi> given to them, whereby to <hi>Believe,</hi> and to <hi>Obey</hi> the Goſpel. They
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110696:8"/>rightly add, at <hi>p.</hi> 55. We no where meet in Scripture any Promiſe, by which God hath bound himſelf to impart his Grace to <hi>All</hi> and every One.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Farthermore, the ſame excellent <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage</hi> teaches, at <hi>p.</hi> 27. that 'tis a Suppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without any good ground, that all <hi>Infants</hi> are ſaved. It ſaith, that thoſe Infants who are ſaved, are ſaved by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of their Election; which reſpecteth not <hi>the Age</hi> of Perſons, but only looketh upon the common heap of <hi>Fallen Mankind,</hi> out of which it chooſeth.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>And concerning ſuch Chooſing or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, it teaches, at <hi>p.</hi> 34. that <hi>Grace</hi> doth find ſome whom it Adopteth, out of <hi>the moſt Wicked,</hi> and at their <hi>laſt End;</hi> while <hi>Many</hi> who ſeem <hi>leſs Guilty,</hi> have no part in this <hi>Gift.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Therefore when <hi>All</hi> are ſaid to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed; or when 'tis ſaid, Chriſt died for <hi>All,</hi> or ſuch like Expreſſions are uſed; this is to be underſtood of <hi>All ſorts,</hi> or orders of Men and Women. He died for High and Low, for Old Men and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, for Youth and Middle-age, for Rich and Poor, for Wiſe and Unwiſe; for <hi>all theſe ſorts,</hi> for ſome particular Perſons of <hi>all</hi> theſe; for ſuch of <hi>all</hi> theſe ſorts as are Elected.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>And thoſe whoever they be, who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend any farther than this, the Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion purchaſed by Chriſt, are <hi>Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>But <hi>Arminianiſm</hi> is only a Limb of <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianiſm;</hi> as a Map of a Province or King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, is but a Limb of a Quarter-map, or of a Map of the whole World. For <hi>Arminians</hi> have borrowed, all they have, both Doctrine and Argument, from the <hi>Socinians</hi> or <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians.</hi> And for that reaſon, it muſt be farther ſaid, that Such as extend the Redemption by Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond what is above declared, are (ſo far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth) <hi>Socinianiz'd,</hi> have departed from the Articles of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, and from <hi>the Suffrage</hi> of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Divines at <hi>Dort.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <div type="notes">
                  <head>The Notes.</head>
                  <p>They tell us, that God ſo Imputed the ſingle Tranſgreſſion of <hi>one</hi> Man, to <hi>all</hi> Men, as to make <hi>all</hi> Men thereupon obnoxious to the Three Deaths, Temporal, Spiritual and Eternal: but that ſoon <hi>Repenting</hi> him of this Rigour, he took up <hi>a Contrary</hi> Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, even to Redeem <hi>all</hi> Men. Well, do they hold of that Mind? For if they do, 'tis no very Hurtful <hi>Tragi-comedy;</hi> becauſe however Unjuſtly <hi>all</hi> Men were Condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet if they are <hi>all</hi> Pardoned, they have been more <hi>Scared</hi> than <hi>Hurt.</hi> But the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (it ſeems) is otherways; for when God reſolves to Redeem <hi>all</hi> Men, the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, he intends to Redeem <hi>Some;</hi> and farther in Electing or Chooſing thoſe <hi>Some,</hi> his Election oft-times is from <hi>the moſt wicked;</hi> and thoſe alſo, at their <hi>laſt End,</hi> or when they have ſinned as long as they can. In a word, of thoſe Few whom God is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to Redeem from that Ruine, which his Imputation of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Sin to them brought on them; he chooſes, They ſay, the <hi>leaſt Worthy</hi> for Objects of the <hi>Higheſt</hi> Mercy, and exerciſes the uttermoſt Unjuſtice and Cruelty, on thoſe that are Better, or however <hi>not ſo bad.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let us conſider theſe two Notable pieces of <hi>Orthodox Doctrine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. God hath Elected to Salvation, and has Redeemed only <hi>Some</hi> of thoſe Many, who were undone by his Imputation of another Man's Tranſgreſſion to them.</p>
                  <p>Now though <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> deny there was any need of a Redeemer, to reſcue us from <hi>Adam</hi>'s Tranſgreſſion, or the Puniſhment thereof; becauſe neither could that Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion be Imputed to us, nor could we be juſtly Puniſh'd for it; yet, on other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, we own there was need of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer. As, to reconcile the World to the one True God, from whom they were departed by an Univerſal Idolatry; and to reconcile God to the World, for that, and <hi>Other</hi> Actual Sins, and divers other Reaſons.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110696:9"/>But we ſay alſo, that whatſoever was <hi>done</hi> or <hi>ſuffer'd</hi> by Chriſt the Redeemer or Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, was equally done <hi>for all</hi> Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, none excepted.</p>
                  <p>We deny not that Holy Scripture ſpeaketh of <hi>the Elect;</hi> but we ſay, it means not thereby, ſome few certain Perſons choſen out of the reſt of Mankind, to Eternal Life, while all others are doomed to Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, or leſt in an incapacity of Salvation. But <hi>the Elect are all Such as turn to God:</hi> all ſuch are by him Elected, that is, <hi>choſen and deſigned for Salvation;</hi> and he would have all Men and Women to be of that number; if they are not, it proceeds from their own Negligence or Wilfulneſs, not from <hi>Adam,</hi> much leſs from God.</p>
                  <p>This is moſt clearly the Doctrine taught in Holy Scripture; even, that the Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Chriſt, is intended for <hi>All;</hi> John 6.51. <hi>The Bread which I give,</hi> ſaith our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>is my Fleſh: which I give for the Life of the WORLD.</hi> The <hi>beloved</hi> Diſciple ſaith, the Lord Chriſt <hi>was a Propitiation for our Sins; and not for ours only, but for the Sins of the WHOLE World,</hi> 1 John 2.2. St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romans</hi> ſaith; <hi>By the righteouſneſs of one</hi> (even the Lord Chriſt) <hi>the free Giſt is come upon ALL Men, to Juſtification of Life,</hi> Rom. 5.18. The Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſaith; <hi>By the Grace of God, Jeſus Chriſt hath taſted death for EVERY Man,</hi> Heb. 2.9. Or if they want a Text, wherein the very word <hi>Imputed</hi> is found; St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>God by Chriſt reconciled the WORLD to himſelf, not Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting their Tranſgreſſions to them,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.29.</p>
                  <p>To tell us Here, as our Oppoſers do, that the <hi>WORLD,</hi> the <hi>WHOLE</hi> World, <hi>ALL</hi> Men, <hi>EVERY</hi> Man, are only <hi>ſome</hi> Men; and thoſe alſo a very <hi>Few:</hi> what is it, but to give us <hi>a Flat</hi> denial of Scripture; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>an Interpretation</hi> thereof? And I will Here leave it, with the unprejudic'd Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderer; whether theſe Texts do not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently prove this part of the Damnable <hi>Socinian</hi> Hereſy. But they ſay farther.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In chooſing or electing out of the heap of <hi>fallen</hi> Mankind; God's Election or Choice is ſometimes from among <hi>the moſt wicked,</hi> and thoſe alſo at their <hi>laſt end,</hi> or after they have ſinned as long as they can.</p>
                  <p>The next thing that we may expect from ſome Men, is, that they will write a <hi>Pane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyrick</hi> in Praiſe of the Devil.</p>
                  <p>If they had ſaid, that the Election for which they contend, is made by the Devil, or falls upon Perſons by chance of the <hi>Dice,</hi> it had been credible, that Redemption and Salvation is <hi>the chance</hi> of <hi>the moſt wicked,</hi> and at their <hi>laſt end.</hi> But to ſay People are <hi>elected</hi> to Salvation, and that by God; and yet that they are <hi>the moſt wicked,</hi> and at their <hi>laſt end,</hi> who are elected and ſaved, is not ſaid without ſuch manifeſt Impiety, that I will not now ſtand to diſpute againſt it, but leave it with every ſincere Lover of God, to judg betwixt us and our Oppoſers.</p>
                  <p>But this one thing I will obſerve, that when they were loading their Maker with ſuch ſcandalous Imputations; they ſhould have ſo contrived their <hi>Calumnies,</hi> as to be ſelf-conſiſtent, and not contradictory to one another, as they are in this Article. For of what <hi>worſe</hi> or <hi>worſt</hi> Men and Women elected to Salvation do they dream, when themſelves have before aſſured us, that the Imputation of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Sin to us makes All averſe to <hi>all</hi> Good, and inclined to <hi>all</hi> Evil? Of ſuch Perſons there is neither <hi>worſe</hi> nor <hi>worſt,</hi> but all are bad alike: ſo bad, that Satan himſelf neither is nor can be worſe. If we all have ſuch an Inclination to Evil <hi>only,</hi> and to <hi>every</hi> kind of Evil, as is neither reſtrained nor corrected, but by an <hi>extraordinary</hi> and <hi>particular</hi> Grace of God; it unavoidably follows, that all are bad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like; and that 'tis a Contradiction to ſay, the worſt or <hi>the moſt wicked</hi> are choſen to be Subjects of the Grace of Redemption, and of a Pre-eternal Election.</p>
                  <p>'Tis no manner of Evaſion here to ſay, that <hi>the Reſtraining Grace</hi> which God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows (more or leſs) on every Perſon, even on the Reprobate, hath ſeveral degrees: and from hence it comes to paſs, that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110696:9"/>ſome are not <hi>ſo bad</hi> as the reſt. For ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 'tis not their own <hi>Choice</hi> or <hi>Act,</hi> but merely the <hi>Momentary</hi> Grace blown into them, that reſtrains any from any ſort of Wickedneſs; it can no more be ſaid of ſuch, that one is better, or <hi>leſs bad</hi> than another, than a <hi>chained</hi> Lion can be ſaid to be tamer, or <hi>leſs fierce,</hi> than a Lion who is <hi>looſe,</hi> and <hi>at full liberty.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Satisfaction.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>WHen the Divine Wiſdom and Goodneſs had determined to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem <hi>all</hi> Men; that is, ſome of <hi>all ſorts,</hi> and of <hi>every Order</hi> of Men, from the damning Imputation of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion to them: to this end, it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary that a full Reparation ſhould be firſt made to the Bleſſed Trinity for that Tranſgreſſion of <hi>Adam;</hi> and that a Puniſhment, <hi>equivalent</hi> to the Puniſhment or threefold Death, which <hi>Adam</hi> had drawn on himſelf and on his Poſterity, ſhould be undergone by ſome Perſon or Perſons, in the ſtead and place of <hi>Adam,</hi> and his Deſcendents.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>It is true, there is no ſuch <hi>Vindictive Juſtice</hi> in God, that He could not by his <hi>Mercy</hi> forgive this Tranſgreſſion, or any other: but in the caſe before us, God is to be conſidered as <hi>a Righteous Governour,</hi> who would not ſuffer his Law to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed and violated, without a full <hi>Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi> to his Honour and Juſtice by the Offenders, or ſome other on behalf of the Offenders. For this reaſon it was, that 'twas neceſſary to find out a Perſon or Perſons, who ſhould undergo the threefold Death for Mankind, or other ways make an <hi>Equivalent</hi> to the Juſtice of God.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Perſon undergoing the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or the Equivalent, muſt be a Righteous Perſon, elſe he would need one to ſatisfy for himſelf. Nay, he muſt be a Perſon of <hi>Infinite</hi> both Merit and Dignity, elſe he could not merit Heaven for ſo many; nor could his Sufferings be accepted inſtead of ſo many as were obnoxious, and obliged to undergo the threefold Death.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The <hi>Expedient</hi> therefore at length re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved on by the Bleſſed Trinity, for the Redemption of Mankind, was this, That <hi>a Righteous</hi> Perſon, of <hi>Infinite</hi> Dignity and Merit, ſhould be ſubſtituted to the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment deſerved by Sinners, in the room, ſtead and place of Sinners.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>This was judged more agreeable to the Majeſty of God, as Governour of the World, than <hi>either</hi> to forgive to <hi>Adam</hi> his Tranſgreſſion, and to his Deſcendents God's Imputation of it to them; <hi>or</hi> than to inflict on him or them any <hi>leſs</hi> Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (as ſuppoſe ſome Temporal Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity) than the threefold Death. Which thing God might have done, either by his Mercy, as a Maker and Father, or by his Authority and Prerogative, as a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign and Governour.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>'Tis true, there is a wonderful depth of Myſtery, never to be fathom'd by Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Underſtanding, in this manner of proceeding. And Human Wiſdom would (without doubt) have choſe, either to <hi>forgive</hi> the Sin, or to <hi>abate</hi> ſomewhat of the Puniſhment, rather than have ſubſtituted in the room of the Wicked and Worthleſs, a Perſon <hi>infinitely</hi> Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and Worthy, even tho ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhould be ſuppoſed to have offered himſelf to the Puniſhment. <hi>But my Thoughts are not your Thoughts, neither are your Ways my Ways, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Iſa. 55.8.</q>
               </p>
               <div type="notes">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:110696:10"/>
                  <head>The Notes.</head>
                  <p>In their Doctrine of <hi>Original</hi> Sin, our Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers feign, that Almighty God imputes the <hi>one</hi> Sin of <hi>one</hi> Man to <hi>all</hi> Men, and concludes them thereupon under the three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſold Death, or <hi>three Deaths:</hi> but in this Doctrine of <hi>the Satisfaction,</hi> they tell us of a <hi>contrary</hi> Prodigy, that he imputes <hi>all</hi> the Sins of <hi>all</hi> Men to <hi>one</hi> Man; and what is yet a greater Monſter, ſays on him alone a Puniſhment <hi>equivalent</hi> to the three Deaths (Temporal, Spiritual and Eternal) of all Mankind.</p>
                  <p>We might call this the Trinitarians <hi>Fetch-back,</hi> if it were not, that the Interpretation they give of this Doctrine, is contrary to the Doctrine it ſelf. One would think, if we might judg of their meaning by what they ſay, that the Doctrine of <hi>the Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> made a compleat Amends for the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Original</hi> Sin; that is, that the (ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed) Satisfaction by Chriſt did (as it were) <hi>fetch-back</hi> the Damage and Loſſes occaſioned (they ſay) by the Sin of <hi>Adam.</hi> But 'tis not ſo: for tho (they ſay) the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer was able to ſuffer, and did actually ſuffer <hi>an Equivalent</hi> to the three Deaths of all Mankind; yet (ſay they farther) nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Merit nor his Sufferings do any good but only to a few, that is, to the Elect.</p>
                  <p>As to the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> they moſt thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and devoutly own, profeſs and publiſh, that the Lord Chriſt underwent the greateſt of Labours and Sufferings for poor wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Apoſtate Mankind. He made himſelf an Oblation, an <hi>Expiatory</hi> Sacrifice on the <hi>Altar</hi> of the Groſs for our Sins, to reconcile us to God, and (in ſome reſpects) God to us. But we ſay, that his Labours and Sufferings on our behalf were not (as Trinitarians teach) deſigned <hi>as a Puniſhment</hi> laid on him in our ſtead, becauſe <hi>Puniſhment is the Evil of Suffering, inflicted for the Evil of doing;</hi> and the Lord Chriſt having <hi>done no Sin,</hi> as the Holy Scriptures expreſly teach, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3. it neceſſarily follows, that what he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derwent, were purely <hi>Labours</hi> and <hi>Sufferings,</hi> not <hi>Puniſhment.</hi> And for thoſe Sufferings we ſay further; it has pleaſed God by way of Recompence, <hi>highly to exalt him, and give him a Name above every Name,</hi> Phil. 2.9.</p>
                  <p>Nor was the Oblation or Sacrifice which the Lord Chriſt made of himſelf, on our behalf, an Oblation made (as our Oppoſers contend) <hi>to the Juſtice of God,</hi> or by way of full Reparation to God's Juſtice; but, as all other Sacrifices formerly were, an Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Application <hi>to the Mercy of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For this Doctrine of ours, we judg the following Reaſons to be ſuch Proofs as muſt needs be allowed, by every one that conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders them freely and impartially.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. One Man could not poſſibly be judged <hi>an Equivalent,</hi> for ſuch an immenſe number of Sinners as were all of them obliged to be as righteous as he; and becauſe they were not ſo, were liable to Puniſhment; therefore it was not <hi>to the Juſtice of God,</hi> that the Lord Chriſt offered himſelf for thoſe Sinners <hi>as an Equivalent, but to God's Mercy,</hi> by way of <hi>humble ſuit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. If <hi>one</hi> Man can be conceived to be an <hi>Equivalent</hi> for <hi>all</hi> Men; yet if the Sufferings (or as our Oppoſers ſpeak, the Puniſhment) he underwent, was not equivalent to the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment due to them; then it muſt not be ſaid, he tendred himſelf to the Juſtice of God, but only to his Mercy, on behalf of the Offenders, and inſtead of their Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Puniſhment, as well as the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſuffering, muſt be equivalent, elſe Juſtice will refuſe it; but Goodneſs or Mercy may admit of it. But now, who ſees not that the <hi>Temporal</hi> Sufferings and <hi>three days</hi> Death of the Lord Chriſt, were far from being equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent to the Death Temporal, Spiritual and Eternal, of ſo much as <hi>one</hi> Man.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Uniratians will never detract from the Dignity of our Saviour's Perſon; they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg with the Scriptures, that <hi>God was with him;</hi> nay, <hi>God</hi> (by his Spirit) <hi>was in him.</hi> But if they could alſo add, as Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians do, that the Humanity of Chriſt was one Perſon with God; yet ſeeing only
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110696:10"/>the Humanity could ſuffer or die; and ſeeing no Union of a Man with God, can exalt <hi>Humanity</hi> to be <hi>Divinity,</hi> or make that to be <hi>Infinite</hi> which of its own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is <hi>Finite;</hi> therefore the Temporal Sufferings and three days Death of a meer Human Nature, cannot be equivalent to the Death Temporal, Spiritual and Eternal, which is <hi>an Infinite</hi> Puniſhment, of all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, no nor of one Man.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. But if it were admitted that <hi>one</hi> Man was ſo <hi>dignified,</hi> by the Inhabitation of God in him, as to be an Equivalent for all Men; admitting alſo, that the three days Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Death of ſuch a Man, amounts to as much as the Deaths Temporal and Spiritual, and the Eternal Damnation of all Mankind: What will follow hereupon? It will follow, that God is obliged in Equity, to releaſe all Mankind from all the three Deaths, Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, Spiritual and Eternal; elſe He hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived an Equivalent on behalf of Mankind, without diſcharging thoſe for whom He received it; which is contrary to <hi>Equity,</hi> nay, to <hi>Juſtice.</hi> For <hi>in Equity</hi> an Equivalent ought to diſcharge the Perſon, whether he be <hi>Offender</hi> or <hi>Debtor:</hi> but if the Equivalent be not only tendred, but accepted alſo on be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the <hi>Debtor</hi> or <hi>Offender,</hi> the Offender hath Wrong done him, if he is not immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately diſcharged of his Puniſhment, and the Debtor of his Debt. But do Trinitarians pretend, or dare they, that God doth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge Mankind from the three Deaths, on the Oblation and Sacrifice of himſelf, made by the Lord Chriſt on their behalf? By no means, they own we are not <hi>at all</hi> diſcharged from Death Temporal, but <hi>in ſome part</hi> from Death Spiritual, and only <hi>a few Perſons</hi> from Death Eternal. It follows, that the Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Death of our Saviour were not in deed an Equivalent to the three Deaths of Mankind.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. To add now no more. The Unitarian Doctrine is conſiſtent, nay, is the very ſame with what the Scriptures every-where ſay; namely, that Almighty God of his Grace, <hi>the Riches</hi> and <hi>Abundance</hi> of his Grace and Love, has <hi>pardoned</hi> Offenders for Chriſt's ſake, on the Conditions on their part, of Faith, Repentance and Newneſs of Life. But the Trinitarian Doctrine, which ſaith, the Puniſhment laid on the Lord Chriſt, was truly equivalent to the Puniſhment due to all Mankind; doth deprive God our Maker and Father, of the Glory of his <hi>Pardoning Grace and Mercy.</hi> Nay, it ſaith in effect, that we are not beholden to God our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on that account. It ſaith, he hath been harſh, nay, hath been apparently un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, in that he hath received more than an Equivalent for our diſcharge from the three Deaths; and yet he hath not <hi>wholly</hi> releas'd any, and but very few are <hi>at all</hi> releaſed.</p>
                  <p>I will only add; Whereas Trinitarians call the <hi>Sufferings</hi> of the Lord Chriſt a <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> and will have that Puniſhment to be equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent to the Infinite Puniſhment due (they ſay) to Mankind for Sin <hi>Original</hi> and <hi>Actual;</hi> and whereas they call this Doctrine, <hi>the Doctrine of the SATISFACTION by the Lord Chriſt;</hi> they have miſtaken in the Name, as well as in the Thing. 'Tis the Unitarians who, in proper ſpeaking, hold that the Lord Chriſt made <hi>Satisfaction</hi> to God for Sin, not Trinitarians. We ſay, that the Sufferings of the Lord Chriſt not being equivalent in the <hi>exact</hi> Scales of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> for what all Mankind have deſerved, yet God was <hi>ſatisfied</hi> with them; that is, was <hi>graciouſly</hi> pleaſed to accept them, as an Interceſſion on our behalf; and this is the proper Notion of <hi>a Satisfaction.</hi> But Trinitarians, in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Sufferings of Chriſt were <hi>equivalent</hi> to the Demerit of our Sins, were a full Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Juſtice of God for them, do not hold a Satisfaction, but <hi>a Reparation,</hi> or <hi>Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Amends.</hi> The more elegant <hi>Latiniſts</hi> call <hi>Confeſſion, Deprecation,</hi> and ſuch like im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect and partial Reparations and Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by the Name of <hi>Satisfactions.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:110696:11"/>
               <head>Of the Incarnation.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>BEcauſe no other but a Perſon of <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite</hi> Merit and Dignity could ſatisfy the Divine Juſtice for <hi>Adam</hi>'s Tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; therefore the ſecond Perſon of the Bleſſed Trinity, called <hi>the Son,</hi> offered himſelf to undergo <hi>the Equivalent</hi> to that Puniſhment, or threefold Death, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to <hi>Adam</hi> and his Deſcendents: and this Offer was accepted by the other two Perſons of the Trinity. It was agreed that <hi>the Son</hi> ſhould become incarnate in an Human Nature, ſhould be <hi>Whole and All</hi> united to a Finite Man, even the Man Chriſt Jeſus, and be one Perſon with him. By this means the Man Chriſt Jeſus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came of that unſpeakable Merit and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, that one drop of his Blood was an Equivalent to the Eternal Puniſhment of all Mankind in Hell-Fire; and his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and the Merit thereof, was infinitely more than enough for himſelf, it was meritorious of Heaven for never ſo many Sinners.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Son was ſo incarnate in a particular Human Nature, as to be <hi>perſonally</hi> thereto united in the very Womb of the Virgin <hi>Mary:</hi> ſo that <hi>Mary</hi> (as General Councils of the Orthodox have rightly defined) was not only <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or <hi>Mother of Chriſt;</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Mother of God.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>This Incarnation of <hi>the Son</hi> in the Man Chriſt Jeſus, begets alſo ſuch <hi>a Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Idioms</hi> (that is, of Properties and Attributes) between the Divinity and the Humanity of the Lord Chriſt; that we muſt ſay on the one hand, <hi>God was born,</hi> God <hi>ſuffered,</hi> God <hi>died;</hi> as we muſt ſay alſo (on the other hand) the Man Chriſt Jeſus is <hi>Eternal, Omnipotent, Omnipreſent, Creator</hi> of Heaven and Earth. As all <hi>Learned</hi> Divines acknowledg, and Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in particular, has largely proved from <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Councils</hi> of the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox. <hi>Bellar. de Chriſto,</hi> l. 3. c. 9.</q>
               </p>
               <div type="notes">
                  <head>The Notes.</head>
                  <p>The Doctrine of the Incarnation claims the place of all the Trinitarian Doctrines, even of the Trinity it ſelf, in regard of its <hi>Seniority.</hi> For while our Oppoſers were on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Homo-ouſians;</hi> that is, believed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed only <hi>two</hi> Eternal and <hi>Conſubſtantial</hi> Perſons, not having yet <hi>dreamt</hi> that the Holy Spirit is God; in the days of the firſt <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, even then they held the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation of the ſecond of thoſe Perſons. Neither does this Doctrine come behind any of their Doctrines, either in the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, or the Rarity and Strangeneſs of its Wonders and Myſteries: but of theſe, three are more remarkable than the reſt. I will make a ſhort Reflection on each of them.</p>
                  <p>The firſt Wonder is, that an Infinite Perſon is whole and all incarnate in a Finite Nature.</p>
                  <p>Which amounts to this, That <hi>Infinite is leſs than Finite;</hi> for elſe how ſhould Infinite be incarnate, that is, <hi>caſed</hi> in the Finite? But make the greateſt Allowances poſſible, yet the Infinite which is whole and all incarnate in the Finite, can (at moſt) but be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſurate to the Finite; that is, but equal to it. Now theſe are two ſuch Paradoxes, that till our Oppoſers can ſeparate them from their Doctrine of the Incarnation, they will never perſwade that Doctrine to any who make uſe of their Reaſon and Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond great Myſtery or Wonder of this Doctrine is, that the particular Human Nature, in which a Perſon of the Trinity vouchſafed to be incarnate, became thereby of <hi>Infinite</hi> Dignity and Merit, (for 'twas an Equivalent for an <hi>Infinite</hi> number of Men, and for the <hi>Infinite</hi> Puniſhment due to them) and yet ſtill remained and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued a meer and bare Human Nature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:110696:11"/>Which is to ſay, a meer Human Nature continuing and abiding a bare and meer Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Nature, is a Divine Nature. For in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming it hath <hi>Infinite</hi> Dignity and Merit; how much ſoever they may ſay in <hi>words,</hi> 'tis a bare and meer Human Nature; they have <hi>in ſenſe</hi> affirmed 'tis a Divine Nature. For what is <hi>Divine,</hi> but as much as to ſay, <hi>of Infinite Dignity, and Infinite Excellence or Merit?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The third Wonder is, That by Virtue of the Incarnation of a Divine Perſon in an Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Nature, the Divine Perſon (or God) muſt be ſaid to have been <hi>born</hi> in Time, to have <hi>ſuffered</hi> and <hi>died;</hi> and on the contrary, the Humanity, or Man Chriſt Jeſus, muſt be ſaid to have been from all Eternity, to be Omnipotent, Omnipreſent, Creator of all things, and whatſoever elſe is ſaid of God.</p>
                  <p>But that our Oppoſers may not complain that they are miſrepreſented, I muſt own, this is only <hi>the fore part</hi> of the Prodigy; the other end, or <hi>hinder part,</hi> is of a contrary Nature. For tho you muſt <hi>ſay</hi> God was born, God ſuffered, God died; yet (ſaith their Doctrine farther) you are not really to <hi>think</hi> God can be born in Time, can ſuffer, or can die: and on the other hand, you muſt <hi>ſay,</hi> the Man Chriſt Jeſus was from all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, created the World, is Omnipreſent and Omnipotent; but you are not ſo to <hi>think.</hi> The reaſon is, becauſe the Communication of the Properties of the Divinity to the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, and of the Humanity to the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, is not <hi>real,</hi> but only <hi>nominal,</hi> or in words.</p>
                  <p>Now Unitarians being but <hi>plain</hi> Fellows, and having <hi>Country</hi> Conſciences, like not this juggling, that we muſt <hi>ſay</hi> one thing, and muſt <hi>think</hi> or mean another. Yet becauſe we ought to yield to hard things for <hi>Peace</hi> ſake: if our Oppoſers are content that we may do ſo alſo in the other Articles; that is, if they are content that we only <hi>ſay</hi> as is ſaid in thoſe Articles, and may declare at the ſame time that we <hi>think</hi> the contrary; and if Trinitarians will alſo ſo do in thoſe Articles, we will comply with them in this third Wonder (or Myſtery) of the Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
                  <p>And this is the only Compoſition that can poſſibly be agreed to in theſe Controverſies, without renouncing our Chriſtianity, our reaſonable Faculties and our Senſes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Grace.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>IT is true, the Lord Chriſt (God and Man in one Perſon) paid down a more than ſufficient Ranſom for the Actual De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance of a thouſand Worlds, from the Imputation of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Sin, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of that Imputation, even the three Deaths; yet the Ranſom was not accepted for <hi>all,</hi> but only for the Elect; nor yet was it accepted for Deliverance from <hi>the whole</hi> Puniſhment, but only from <hi>part</hi> of it, For no Man is thereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from ſuch a ſhare of <hi>Spiritual</hi> Death, as to be able to <hi>do</hi> a good Action, or <hi>think</hi> a good Thought, without an immediate and particular Aſſiſtance or GRACE of God's Spirit, <hi>beginning, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing</hi> and <hi>perfecting</hi> ſuch good Action or Thought <hi>in</hi> him, and <hi>by</hi> him. As hath been often defined and concluded in the <hi>Councils</hi> of the Orthodox, in oppoſition to the Hereſy of <hi>Pelagius,</hi> revived by <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians</hi> and <hi>Arminians.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <div type="notes">
                  <head>The Notes.</head>
                  <p>After they have tried their Skill in miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſenting and deforming the true Idea we ought to have of God, and of his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and Attributes: our Oppoſers pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to <hi>calumniate</hi> Human Nature, <hi>the Image of God,</hi> and will have it to be <hi>the Image of the Devil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They tell us, we come into the World ſo depraved in all our Faculties and Powers,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:110696:12"/>that we cannot <hi>do</hi> any good Action, no, nor <hi>think</hi> a good Thought, without a particular and extraordinary Grace of God, <hi>beginning, continuing and perfecting</hi> ſuch good Action or Thought <hi>in</hi> us, and <hi>by</hi> us.</p>
                  <p>In ſober ſadneſs, is this the Character of that ſort of Creature, of whom the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>be is made in the ſimilitude of God?</hi> James 3.9. Or is it the very Deſcription of the Devil himſelf, if at leaſt it be not a Calumny even of him? Will God own ſuch a Creature as his Similitude, as has a natural Impotence to all that is holy and good, and a violent and perpetual Biaſs to Evil only, and to every kind of Evil?</p>
                  <p>Yes, they ſay our Likeneſs to God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts not in a Capacity to Holineſs, or ought that good is; but in <hi>the Dominion we have over ſome Creatures in this lower World.</hi> But by this account of our Likeneſs to God, he that is <hi>moſt of all unlike to God,</hi> is much more the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude and Image of God, than Man is; the Dominion and Power of Satan is incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably greater and larger than Man's is; therefore in their Hypotheſis he is more the Similitude of God than Man is.</p>
                  <p>But as abſurd as theſe things are, I will not now inſiſt on them, but content my ſelf to acquaint the Reader with ſome of the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Reaſons of the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> why they hold that Man is a <hi>free</hi> Agent, as capable of doing Good as Evil; nay, <hi>more capable of the former,</hi> becauſe he <hi>has more reaſon for it,</hi> than of the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; not the Slave to only one of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries, but at abſolute liberty towards both.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Our <hi>Bluſhes</hi> and <hi>Remorſes</hi> for having acted at any time otherways than we ought, are Teſtimonies and Witneſſes of our <hi>certain</hi> and <hi>internal</hi> Conſciouſneſs, that we could have done, as Religion and Duty require of us; that is, could have forbore that Evil, and have done the contrary Good.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Deliberation</hi> and <hi>Conſultation,</hi> what and how we are to act, argue alſo, not only that we are <hi>free,</hi> but that we are ſenſible we are ſo.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. We experience that our Piety and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue are our own Work, by the Difficulty we <hi>feel,</hi> and the ſlow Progreſs we are able to make in attaining thoſe Habits, and in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing the contrary Habits.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. If Men are good, not by a ſpontaneous Choice or Power of their own, but only by an extraordinary and immediate Aid: no to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable reaſon can be given, why we ſhould not <hi>always</hi> be acted to Good, or why we are but <hi>partially</hi> and <hi>imperfectly</hi> Good? Is it credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that God ſhould do his own Work in us, after a <hi>deſultory, inconſtant</hi> and <hi>imperſect</hi> manner?</p>
                  <p n="5">5. What Piety or Vertue is it; or how can God love or eſteem any Perſon, whether Him or Her, for that well-doing, or that abſtinence from Evil, which was not their own <hi>Choice, Will,</hi> or <hi>Diſcretion,</hi> but the Work and Effect ſolely of God's <hi>Grace,</hi> acting <hi>by</hi> them, or <hi>in</hi> them?</p>
                  <p n="6">6. That every good Thought and Action, is not an Inſpiration, or the Gift or Grace of God, is confirmed by this; that God doth ſometimes diſallow and forbid ſome good In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions and Actions of his Servants. Thus, 'twas a good Thought and Intention in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> that he would <hi>build an Houſe for the Lord,</hi> a Temple for God's publick Worſhip and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: 'twas ſo good a Thought and Purpoſe, that it was rewarded with a Promiſe from God, that God would <hi>build</hi> David<hi>'s Houſe, i. e.</hi> would eſtabliſh and confirm his Family on the Throne of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael.</hi> But as good a Thought as that of <hi>David</hi> was, it came ſolely from <hi>David,</hi> not from God; for in that very Context, (2 <hi>Sam. Ch.</hi> 7.) God diſallowed and forbad it; declaring withal, that He had reſerved that Work for <hi>Solomon</hi> the Son of <hi>David.</hi> No one will be ſo <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian,</hi> as to deny, that 'twas a good Thought and Action in St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, that they attempted to preach the Goſpel in <hi>Bithynia:</hi> but it came from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, not from God; for the Text ſays, God ſuffer'd them not ſo to do, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.7.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. If our Caſe were ſuch, with reſpect to Good and Evil, as our Oppoſers pretend; that is, if all the Good we do, and all the Evil we forbear, is only by <hi>a daily, hourly and momentary Grace,</hi> (for ſo they affect to ſpeak) inſpired, infuſed, or blown into us: The
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:110696:12"/>Words of the Divine Law ſhould be directed <hi>to God's Grace</hi> in us, not <hi>to us.</hi> But now this is not only not ſo, but the Phraſe and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion uſed in the Law or Commandment plainly ſuppoſes, that we can obey by our own proper Powers. Such (in particular) is that remarkable Text, at <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.31, 32. <hi>Make you a new Heart, and a new Spirit; for why will ye die, O Houſe of</hi> Iſrael? <hi>I have no pleaſure in the Death of him that dieth; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore turn your ſelves, and live ye.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8. Our Ability to Good as well as Evil, is evinced alſo by this, that God declares he will puniſh the neglect of Duty, and every evil Doer, after a moſt terrible and condign man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. This would be too apparently unjuſt and tyrannical, if himſelf hath ſo made us, that we cannot do that Duty, or forbear that Evil, without a particular and extraordinary Grace and Aid, which is in the Gift and Power of God only, and which he refuſeth or omitteth to beſtow on us. Our Oppoſers deny, that we can ſo much as <hi>pray</hi> for that Grace or Aid of God, by which to do Good and forbear Evil: for they ſay, the very <hi>Affectus orandi, the Inclination or Intent to pray,</hi> is purely the Gift of God. As for <hi>the Word</hi> and <hi>Sacraments,</hi> another means for obtaining God's Grace, we ſhall ſee hereafter, that our Oppoſers make <hi>the outward</hi> Word of no Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy, aſcribing all to <hi>the inward</hi> Word, which is not at all in our Power; and in order to any Benefit by <hi>the Sacraments</hi> ſo called, they require a great many previous Graces which are only in the Hand of God.</p>
                  <p>So that after all their Subterfuges, Evaſions and Shifts, their Doctrine concerning <hi>Grace</hi> amounts to this; God will puniſh Men eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in Hell-Fire for not doing, and for not forbearing what 'twas not in them to do or forbear, without ſuch <hi>an extraordinary</hi> Grace of God, as was wholly in him to give, and not at all in them to attain or get.</p>
                  <p>As to the Texts by them alledged to prove that all is done by the Grace of God, and that <hi>we</hi> are impotent, and averſe alſo to <hi>all</hi> Good: They have been often told by the <hi>Socinians</hi> and <hi>Remonſtrants,</hi> and in the Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the excellent <hi>Grotius,</hi> how thoſe Texts are to be underſtood. To them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I refer, without ingaging in ſo long and tedious a Digreſſion.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Word and Sacraments.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>NOW that <hi>the Elect</hi> may obtain the before mentioned Grace of God, by which to <hi>believe</hi> aright, and to <hi>do</hi> that which Good is, the Trinity have appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>the Word</hi> and <hi>Sacraments.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>A Sacrament conſiſts of two Parts, <hi>an outward viſible Sign, and an inward inviſible Grace or Energy.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The viſible Sign of the Sacrament of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is <hi>Water;</hi> the inward <hi>Grace</hi> is <hi>New Birth,</hi> unto Faith and Righteouſneſs. By this Sacrament even Infants are regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or <hi>born again</hi> by the Spirit co-opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; that is to ſay, Faith, Obedience, and other ſaving Graces are conferred in this Sacrament on (Elect) Infants.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>In the Sacrament of <hi>the Supper,</hi> the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Sign is <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine;</hi> the inward Energy, or Grace accompanying it, is, firſt <hi>Remiſſion of Sins;</hi> next, <hi>the refreſhing</hi> and ſtrengthening our Souls in Faith and other Graces. Theſe things are amply and often taught us by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, both in the publick Catechiſm, and in the Offices or Forms of adminiſtring Baptiſm and the Lord's-Supper.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>The Word</hi> is another appointed means of Grace; but no one is to think that 'tis by <hi>Arguments</hi> uſed by a Preacher, or by <hi>the Rewards</hi> or <hi>Puniſhments</hi> held forth in the Word, whether <hi>written</hi> or <hi>preach'd;</hi> or ſuch-like external and human means, that our Minds are <hi>ſavingly</hi> convinced, or our Wills and Affections <hi>rightly</hi> diſpoſed. No,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110696:13"/>no, the inward and ineffable Word which God himſelf ſpeaks to the Heart, and which towards <hi>the Elect</hi> accompanies the Word preach'd or read, when and as oft as God pleaſes; this is that only Word which begets Faith, worketh Obedience, and (in one word) that whole Renovation or Change, which denominateth a Man or Woman, the Child or Servant of God.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>And thus much is plainly and undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly intimated in the Collects, and other Prayers and Offices of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Service-Book, and is the known Doctrine of all the Orthodox, of all indeed but <hi>Socinians,</hi> and ſuch as are (more or leſs) <hi>Socinianiz'd.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Service-Book and the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles are ſo clearly for theſe Doctrines, that it hath occaſioned this Declaration of what may be meant when Men ſubſcribe to the Articles, Homilies and Service-Book, to be favourably received, even this, that Men ſubſcribe (not to the Truth, but) to <hi>the uſe</hi> of the Service-Book; and again, they ſubſcribe to the Articles, as <hi>to Articles of Peace and Communion,</hi> (which they will not publickly impugn in the ſtation of <hi>Preachers</hi>) not as to <hi>Articles of Faith,</hi> or of abſolute and undoubted Verity. This is the ſenſe in which (perhaps) <hi>moſt</hi> Men now ſubſcribe to the Homilies, Articles and Service-Book, and which (upon occaſion) they declare to be the meaning of their Subſcription. But all ſuch are reformed, according to the Model, not of our firſt Reformers, but of <hi>Socinus, Arminius</hi> and <hi>Epiſcopius,</hi> whatſoever the Station may be that they hold in the Church.</q>
               </p>
               <div type="notes">
                  <head>The Notes.</head>
                  <p>The Sum of this Doctrine is; tho we are ſo made by God, as to be by Nature impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to <hi>all</hi> Good, and diſpoſed to <hi>all</hi> Evil; yet to cure <hi>the Elect</hi> (tho not wholly, yet in part) of this corrupt and depraved Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Minds and Souls, God has ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the Word and Sacraments. Which are a ſort of means, that work not by any <hi>natural</hi> Energy <hi>of their own,</hi> nor by any Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, Sutableneſs or Agreeableneſs to our Powers, Faculties or Natures; but by a <hi>Theurgical, Teleſtick</hi> and <hi>Myſtical</hi> Operation. Which is to ſay, they work on our Minds as <hi>Spells, Charms</hi> and <hi>Incantations</hi> (and ſuch like) obtain their (pretended) Effects; namely, by a <hi>Praeternatural</hi> Power, <hi>extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily</hi> given to them by God, or by thoſe Spirits that preſide over ſuch Affairs.</p>
                  <p>Let a Man in black ſprinkle you with ſome of the Church's <hi>Water,</hi> or give you a bit of <hi>Bread,</hi> or a ſup of <hi>Wine,</hi> over which he has pronounced the Wonder-working Words, preſcribed in Mother-<hi>Church</hi>'s Ritual; tho <hi>by Nature</hi> you are as bad as the Devil, you ſhall preſently be inclined to as much Good, as will ſave you from Hell, and qualify you for Heaven. And this no leſs certainly, if you are one of <hi>the Elect,</hi> for elſe the Churches <hi>Incantation</hi> produces only a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Effect, and a falſe Appearance of Good: no leſs certainly, I ſay, than by tying <hi>the Norman</hi> Knot, you may gain the Love of the Perſon you deſire, or by other Devices recorded in the learned Books (ſo Fools e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem them) of <hi>Magick,</hi> you may cauſe Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, raiſe Winds, and do a thouſand other Feats, which have no more natural or real Agreement with thoſe Cauſes that are ſaid to produce them, than Faith and Obedience have with a bit of <hi>Bread,</hi> or with a ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of <hi>Water.</hi> Therefore when St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> defined a Sacrament to be <hi>the outward viſible Sign of an inward inviſible Grace or Energy:</hi> the good <hi>Father</hi> ſhould have conſidered, that this is the Definition of <hi>a Charm,</hi> not of <hi>a Goſpel-Sacrament.</hi> For a Charm is a bare <hi>outward viſible Sign,</hi> that has no natural or real Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the Effect; and if the Effect prove for the good of the Perſon concerned, it may be called <hi>the inward inviſible Grace</hi> of ſuch Sign or Charm; as when the Effect is to beget <hi>Love,</hi> or ſuch like. But if the Effect of the Charm be hurtful, as to <hi>kill,</hi> or ſuch like, then it muſt be called <hi>the Energy,</hi> not the Grace of the Charm; as that <hi>damning</hi> Quality or Power which our Oppoſers im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:110696:13"/>to the Sacrament of <hi>the Supper,</hi> when not received aright, cannot be called <hi>the Grace</hi> of that Sacrament, but only <hi>the Energy.</hi> So that let them turn themſelves which way ſoever they can, they have turned the Goſpel-Sacraments (as I ſaid before) into Charms and Spells.</p>
                  <p>Now on the contrary, Unitarians think of the Sacraments <hi>reverently,</hi> not <hi>extravagantly</hi> or <hi>ſuperſtitiouſly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They like not indeed the word <hi>Sacraments,</hi> becauſe 'tis no Scripture-word; and becauſe the <hi>Criticks</hi> have noted, that 'tis a very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper Term or Name, to denote the <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies</hi> of Baptiſm, and of commemorating the Paſſion and Death of our Saviour. But they will not quarrel about words, if the Things ſignified be agreeable to Reaſon or Holy Scripture.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We think</hi> that <hi>Baptiſm</hi> was a Ceremony or Rite appointed by our Saviour, for divers moſt weighty Reaſons; whereof this was the chief, to initiate or enter <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Heathens</hi> into the Chriſtian Church. It was a very proper and ſignificant Rite and Ceremony: for the waſhing and cleanſing the Body in Water, doth very aptly ſignify that <hi>Repentance,</hi> and thoſe Purpoſes of <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Purity,</hi> which ſuch as enter themſelves into the Chriſtian Church, or are born in that Church, ſhould profeſs and practiſe. He that comes to be baptized, that is, to be <hi>waſhed in Water,</hi> doth thereby profeſs, he will in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>purge</hi> his Mind and Conſcience, and his whole Converſation from Impurity and Wickedneſſes of all ſorts, by delivering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf up to the Inſtitution and Guidance of that Goſpel, which was given by <hi>the Father</hi> (or God) as its Author, was brought by <hi>the Son</hi> (our Lord Chriſt) as the Meſſenger, and confirmed by the Holy Spirit (or the Power and Inſpiration of God) by abundance of Signs, Miracles and Wonders.</p>
                  <p>Therefore according to the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> 'tis not this Sacrament that worketh ought in us, much leſs <hi>renews, regenerates</hi> and <hi>changes</hi> our Natures; but the Perſon who receives this Sacrament, is to reſolve and purpoſe Renova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Regeneration or Newneſs of Life. This Doctrine we learn form St. <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.21. <hi>The like Figure whereunto, even Baptiſm, doth alſo now ſave us; not the putting away the Filth of the Fleſh,</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> not the meer Ceremony of Baptiſm, that is, of dipping and waſhing in Water) <hi>but the Anſwer of a good Conſcience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God.</hi> That is, if as our Bodies are baptized, or <hi>waſh'd</hi> in Water, ſo alſo we purify our Conſciences of all Diſobedience towards God.</p>
                  <p>From this Explication of Baptiſm ſome have drawn theſe two Corollaries or Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That Baptiſm ſhould be adminiſtred by <hi>dipping</hi> in Water; for by that, cleanſing of the Body is effected, at leaſt is intended and ſignified: but <hi>ſprinkling</hi> doth neither <hi>cleanſe,</hi> nor ſignify cleanſing the Body, and ſo is very improper to ſignify <hi>the Anſwer of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> that is, the cleanſing the Heart and Conſcience from Evil.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That no Perſon is capable of this Rite, but ſuch as can profeſs and intend, the thing ſignified by Baptiſm, even a clean Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and a new Life.</p>
                  <p>As to the Lord's-Supper, every one knows the mighty Wonders aſcribed by our Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers to this Sacrament. <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſay, the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Bread and Wine are changed into the Subſtance of Chriſt's Body. <hi>Lutherans</hi> ſay, they are <hi>conſubſtantiated</hi> with his Body. The Church of <hi>England</hi> goes beyond the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts;</hi> for ſhe ſaith (in the Catechiſm) that <hi>the Body and Blood of Chriſt are VERILY and INDEED taken and received by the Faithful</hi> (not by others) <hi>in the Lord's-Supper.</hi> This implieth ſuch a Real and Univerſal Preſence of our Lord's Body in the Sacrament, as far exceeds the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Tranſubſtantiation; for <hi>that</hi> limits the Preſence to only <hi>the Subſtance</hi> of Chriſt's Body, and excludes <hi>the Accidents;</hi> but this takes in <hi>both.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarian</hi> Doctrine concerning this Sacrament, is plain and ſimple. <hi>We ſay,</hi> our Saviour has told us the meaning of this Sacrament in thoſe words, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.19. <hi>This do in remembrance of me.</hi> And St. <hi>Paul,</hi>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:110696:14"/>1 Cor. 11.26. <hi>As oft as ye eat this Bread, and drink this Cup, ye do ſhew the Lord's Death.</hi> That is, you commemorate and repreſent the ſhedding the Lord's Blood, and the breaking his Body for Mankind.</p>
                  <p>But for the miraculous Effects and Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences aſcribed to the right partaking of this Sacrament, Unitarians can find them no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, but in the Books and Sermons of the <hi>ſuperſtitious Admirers</hi> (I might have ſaid Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters) <hi>of External Things.</hi> 'Tis true, the Apoſtle blameth the <hi>Corinthians</hi> for receiving <hi>unworthily.</hi> But the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthineſs</hi> was their <hi>Drunkenneſs in the very Act of communicating,</hi> that is, of commemorating the Death of our Saviour; and 'tis of this and the like Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders <hi>in the Act of communicating,</hi> that he there bids them to <hi>examine themſelves,</hi> before they preſume to take the Memorials of their Lord's Death.</p>
                  <p>As for thoſe words of our Saviour at <hi>John</hi> 6.53. <hi>Except ye eat the Fleſh of the Son of Man, and drink his Blood, ye have no Life in you,</hi> and divers ſuch-like Expreſſions in that Chapter, eſpecially toward the latter end of it: 'tis certain, and agreed by the moſt Learned Interpreters, (<hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> as well as <hi>Socinians</hi>) that our Saviour is not there ſpeaking of the Sacrament of <hi>the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> which (when he made thoſe Diſcourſes) was not yet inſtituted, but of <hi>believing</hi> in him, and <hi>imitating</hi> his Example. <hi>H. Grotius</hi> hath very judiciouſly and learnedly, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry amply alſo proved this to be the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that Context; and I believe hath ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied as many as have carefully read and conſidered that part of his Annotations. Wherefore I refer to him, and the Engliſh Reader to the Paraphraſe of the late Learned and Pious Dr. <hi>Claget.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Our Oppoſers delight in <hi>marvelous</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines; therefore, as they pretend, that Faith and Newneſs of Life are effected by God in us, by Means ſo unſutable to the Qualities produced, and to the Nature of our Souls, as <hi>Water, Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine:</hi> ſo they aſſure us farther, that the <hi>written</hi> Word and Word preach'd have no Efficacy toward begetting thoſe Effects; but 'tis (ſay they) the <hi>inward</hi> Word, which (<hi>ſometimes, to ſome,</hi> and <hi>in ſome meaſure</hi>) accompanying the Word <hi>written</hi> or <hi>preach'd,</hi> firſt <hi>convinces,</hi> and then <hi>reclaims</hi> Sinners.</p>
                  <p>For my part, I would gladly know what kind of thing an <hi>inward Word</hi> is; I had thought all <hi>Words</hi> had been <hi>outward</hi> Words, and that otherways they could not have been called <hi>Words.</hi> But be that as it will, Unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians are well ſatisfied that the <hi>outward</hi> Word (as our Oppoſers are pleaſed to <hi>Nickname</hi> the Holy Scriptures, and the Word <hi>preach'd</hi>) is ſufficient and effectual (by <hi>the Reaſons</hi> it ſuggeſteth, and the <hi>Rewards</hi> and <hi>Penalties</hi> it propoſeth) to convince and reform our <hi>Reaſonable</hi> Natures, and that <hi>otherways they were not Reaſonable (but Brutiſh) Natures.</hi> This is not ours, but the Doctrine of Holy Scripture, and that in as expreſs and clear Terms as can be deviſed. Firſt, as to the Efficacy of <hi>the written</hi> Word, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Thou haſt known the Holy Scriptures, which are able to make thee wiſe unto Salvation.</hi> Then for the Word <hi>taught,</hi> after St. <hi>Paul</hi> had ſaid, Rom. 10.14. <hi>How ſhall they believe on him, of whom they have not heard? and how ſhall they hear without a Preacher?</hi> He makes this Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion at <hi>ver.</hi> 17. <hi>So then Faith cometh by Hearing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And is it not indeed a very ſtrange Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox of theſe Gentlemen, that the Wiſdom of God ſhould make uſe of <hi>a Means that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth</hi> (they ſay) <hi>no Effect?</hi> If the outward Word produceth no Effect in him that hears or reads, we might as well have been bid to <hi>tell twenty,</hi> in order to the getting Faith, and ſubduing our Luſts, as to hear and meditate of God's Word. And if that be indeed the caſe, 'tis very ſurprizing, that God ſhould expoſtulate after ſuch an angry manner with lazy and negligent Paſtors, and ſhould ſo heartily rouze up others, as 'tis undeniable he doth. Iſa. 56.10. <hi>They are dumb Dogs, that cannot bark, ſleeping, lying down, loving to ſlumber.</hi> Iſa. 58.1. <hi>Cry aloud, ſpare not, lift up thy Voice like a Trumpet; ſhew my People their Tranſgreſſions, and the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael <hi>their Sins.</hi> 1 Cor. 9.16. <hi>Neceſſity is laid upon me; and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:110696:14"/>wo unto me if I preach not the Goſpel.</hi> What needed any thing of all this, if the outward Word is nothing; and 'tis only the inward Word (which is not in the leaſt tied to the other) that only can and does produce the deſired Effect?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>About interpreting Holy Scripture.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>IF it be asked, how it comes to paſs that we differ ſo widely from <hi>the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks</hi> about the Doctrines ſpecified in the foregoing Paragraphs, while both we and they pretend Holy Scripture to be our <hi>Rule,</hi> and the ſole <hi>Judg</hi> of Controverſies and Queſtions about Religion? The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is at hand, even this, That Hereticks being Men of ſome Wit and Learning, and withal <hi>carnal,</hi> are hereupon puffed up, are too proud to ſubmit themſelves to God's <hi>Revelation,</hi> but only as bowed and ſubdued to their <hi>Reaſon.</hi> But 'tis all Mens Duty in a Claſh between Revelation and Reaſon, whether <hi>real</hi> or only <hi>ſeeming,</hi> to ſubmit Reaſon to Revelation, and not ſubject <hi>Divine</hi> Revelation to <hi>Human</hi> Reaſon. 'Tis unpardonable Boldneſs in any, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the <hi>expreſs</hi> words, or <hi>evident</hi> ſenſe of Holy Scripture, becauſe our Reaſon cannot fathom the <hi>depths</hi> of that Divine Book. If I would believe the Doctrine there ſet down, were it not for the Contradiction made to it by Human Reaſon; I am not a Chriſtian otherways than in Name, if I do not receive ſuch Doctrine with <hi>an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit</hi> Faith, without ſeeking to <hi>elude,</hi> or to <hi>correct</hi> it by Reaſon.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>And it is upon this Hinge that all our Controverſies with theſe Hereticks do turn, whether we are to follow <hi>the expreſs</hi> words and <hi>obvious</hi> natural ſenſe of Holy Scripture; or, whether we are to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret Scripture by Reaſon, ſo as to fly to a <hi>Figurative</hi> Senſe, or even to a <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chreſtical</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> ſomewhat <hi>harſh</hi>) Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction or Interpretation, rather than admit any Doctrine that is contrary to Reaſon?</q>
               </p>
               <div type="notes">
                  <head>The Notes.</head>
                  <p>Unitarians think that a <hi>real</hi> Claſh between Revelation and Reaſon is an <hi>abſurd Suppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> but if we muſt put that impoſſible caſe, we think 'tis clear, that Human Reaſon muſt needs be ſubjected to Divine Revelation. But where the Claſh is only ſeeming, that is, where there are ways of reconciling them, as by ſo <hi>interpreting</hi> the Revelation, as to make it agree with Reaſon: we think 'tis as ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd to oppoſe (as Trinitarians do) theſe two Lights to one another; we think in that caſe we ought to uſe the Expedient of <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation.</hi> If the Interpretation muſt be made either by a <hi>Figurative</hi> Senſe, or by ſomewhat <hi>Catachreſtical</hi> (harſh) Conſtruction, yet <hi>'tis always better to ſtrain Words than Things;</hi> and there are particular Reaſons why we ought ſo to do, in interpreting Holy Scripture, and all Interpreters (of all Perſwaſions) do it with Approbation of <hi>All.</hi> Yet this is a thing on which I will not here inſiſt, tho it deſerveth great Conſideration; becauſe this is not, as Trinitarians pretend, our Caſe or Quarrel with them; or <hi>the Hinge on which theſe Controverſies turn.</hi> For we utterly deny, that <hi>the expreſs</hi> Words, or <hi>the obvious</hi> natural Senſe of Holy Scripture, are on the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarian ſide: we never fly (in theſe Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies) <hi>to a Catachreſtical,</hi> or harſh ſenſe; no, nor have at any time need of a <hi>Figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> Senſe, as hath been ſufficiently ſhown in <hi>the brief Hiſtory of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians.</hi> Trinitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans indeed are forced to thoſe Expedients. I do not call them <hi>Shifts,</hi> becauſe 'tis plain, they muſt be ſometimes allowed not only in interpreting Holy Scripture, but in all other Writers and Writings. But ſeeing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:110696:15"/>themſelves are forced to uſe very often thoſe ways of interpreting; eſpecially in inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting the Goſpel of St. <hi>John,</hi> and the moſt part of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles, they have no right to object ſuch kind of interpreting to Unitarians, if indeed we had occaſion for it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The CONCL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SION.</head>
               <p>THeſe things have not been ſaid, God is Witneſs, to <hi>challenge,</hi> much leſs to <hi>affront</hi> other Sects and Denominations of Chriſtians, and leaſt of all the Church of <hi>England.</hi> From which Church the Unitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans have not ſeparated, as other Diſſenters, for ſmall and inconſiderable Cauſes, have done.</p>
               <p>We place not Religion <hi>in worſhipping God by our ſelves,</hi> or after a particular Form or Manner, but <hi>in a right Faith, and a juſt and charitable Converſation:</hi> We approve of known <hi>Forms</hi> of praiſing, and praying to God; as alſo in adminiſtring Baptiſm, the Lord's-Supper, Marriage, and the other Religious <hi>Offices;</hi> we like well of the Diſcipline of the Church by Biſhops and <hi>Parochial</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; we have an Eſteem for the eminent Learning, and exemplary Piety of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming</hi> Clergy. For theſe Reaſons we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with that Church as far as we can, and contribute <hi>our Intereſt</hi> to favour her againſt all others who would take the Chair.</p>
               <p>We would not therefore be underſtood to be <hi>Enemies</hi> to the Church, or as ſeeking to undermine her. Our whole <hi>Pretence</hi> is this, to reform our FAITH <hi>by the Rule of Holy Scripture, in conſiſtence with evident REASON.</hi> And <hi>the deſign</hi> of this Pretence or Endeavour of ours, next to approving our own Souls to God our Judg, is, to vindicate the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chriſtianity from the Inſults of Atheiſts, or other profane Perſons; to take from <hi>ſuch</hi> all <hi>juſt</hi> Exception againſt the moſt holy and wiſe Body of Laws, that the World ever had or can have, even <hi>the Chriſtian Religion.</hi> By making <hi>it</hi> appear to be a moſt <hi>rational</hi> and <hi>conſiſtent</hi> Syſtem, as well in the <hi>Credenda, the Things to be believed,</hi> as in the <hi>Ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>a,</hi> or <hi>Things to be done.</hi> We think this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch a Deſign as ought not to be enterta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> with thoſe <hi>Jealouſies,</hi> and aſperſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thoſe <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies</hi> and <hi>Clamours,</hi> that are every day raiſed againſt us, both by the Pulpit and Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſs.</p>
               <p>We hope that the Reaſons of our Diſſent from the Church in theſe Doctrines, being once known, and well conſidered, and the Honeſty of our Deſign in publiſhing them apparent; our Fellow-Chriſtians will leſs regret our Difference with them about theſe Queſtions, and will at length acknowledg, that however we are miſtaken, yet we are <hi>well-meaning</hi> Brethren.</p>
               <p>Thou <hi>Father,</hi> who governeſt in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the Children of Men, continue to us All, the Means of <hi>rightly</hi> knowing Thee, and of living up to the Precepts of the Goſpel; that we may All at length receive of thee, <hi>the Inheritance incorruptible, undefiled, that fades not away, reſerved in Heaven for us.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:110696:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
